The beginning, deejan baptism be sullied in dire fashion.
A rise then, but do so at once, without delay.
Do not defer your purpose till tonight, or tomorrow,
or later when I have finished what I have to do just now.
The interval may be fatal.
No, this moment, the instant you make your resolution,
you will show by your action that you have taken leave
of your old self and have now begun a new life
with a new destination and a new rail.
living. Arise therefore without fear and say, Lord, let me begin now. Help me for what
you need above all is God's help. Hold fast to your purpose and do not look back. We have
been giving a warning example in Lot's wife who was turned into a pillar of salt when
she looked back. You have cast off your old humanity. Let the rags lie. Like Abraham,
You've heard the voice of the Lord.
Get the out of like...
country and from thy kindred and from thy father's house into the land that I will show thee.
Towards that land hereafter you must direct all your attention.
Tito Kaliander from Way of the Ascetics on Ancient Faith Radio.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those
whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young, host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Welcome back.
to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in a man's Pennsylvania
and my co-host Father Stephen D'Young
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
Now because this episode is releasing
on American Thanksgiving, it is a pre-recorded show.
So don't call this time, save your calls for next time.
That said, we did get some voicemails from some of you
that we will be including in this episode.
So tonight, or actually it's today when I'm recording,
but whatever, you're listening tonight,
We're going to be continuing our...
four parts series on the Christology of the Old Testament.
This is part two.
Last time we talked about the angel of the Lord,
and this time we're going to be discussing
the word of the Lord or the word of God.
This is another phrase that gets people confused sometimes.
What does word of God mean exactly?
Is it the Bible?
Is it Christ?
Can we use the phrase for both?
Well, it turns out that the scripture itself
uses the phrase very consistently.
So this episode is dedicated to taking a close look, not at every single example.
That would be hours and hours long, not that that has ever really stopped us before, of
course.
But we'll be looking at the paradigmatic uses of the word of God or the word of the Lord
in the Bible, which will then tell us something very significant about the Christian faith.
So it's got the word word in there, Father.
So is this just talking about language?
No.
Yeah.
So to come. Yeah, I want to I want to clarify something for the record though.
Okay. We begin. Yeah. Sure.
So I was perfectly willing to come and broadcast live on Thanksgiving night.
I wanted to be with our listeners, right?
As they were covered from gorging on Turkey to celebrate New England puritanism
and their revisionist history of the founding of the country.
But
It's not these two.
I was alone. I was alone in that desire. And so it's it's going to be pre-recorded. Yeah, when people hear this
I'm going to be traveling to see family and our producer Trude will be doing probably good things with
her own family. So yeah, I'll have the night off. I'll probably be watching an old horror movie.
But yeah, so enjoy it. The Detroit Lines will have already lost by that time. Oh
So that's the game with a pointed ball, right?
Yes, the one that looks like Kibbie. Oh, yes. That's right. Yeah. Yeah.
But I wanted I wanted to just lay that out for the right. Okay. So so to begin
I wanted to play one of the voice mails that we got from one of you our listeners
Hi, father's my name is Olga Karpushina. I'm calling from Kazakhstan
My question is.
as a formal linguist, I would want to know when we talk about the word of God, right?
Lord, what realm will that word belong to? In general linguistics, we have two terms.
Lang and Kahol, these terms were coined by our structural linguist, Pachanandus,
issue. And basically, lung would be theoretical like language that pre-exist.
ashrances like a like platonic idea, I would say, whereas the parallel would be individual,
like speech, concrete-revealed language in use. So when we talk about the word,
which category or will that were belong to, would it be the realm of
long of the whole and
If it is to all, if it is pronounced, then who pronounced that?
Who wouldn't be Jesus Christ?
Because he's the only one who has the body or what?
Just curious. Thank you.
Okay, so Olga from Kazakhstan, I think this might be our first call from Kazakhstan, right?
I think, yeah.
At least directly from Kazakhstan.
That we're aware of.
Yeah, so Olga the linguist,
She was asking about whether the sense of the word of the Lord of the...
the word of God, if it could be understood in terms of linguistic theory. Now, I had to dig deep within
my memory banks to even refresh my mind as to exactly what the term she means her using. So,
forgive me, I am not a linguist. I just like to study this stuff that's kind of linguistics adjacent.
But so she was asking about, it's called structuralism, which is a particular theory of linguistics,
that arose in the mid-20th century.
And she mentioned Sossur, who is one of these theorists
from that time.
And he came up with this distinction between,
now he's using the French words long and parol,
which we could translate into English roughly as language
or speech.
So the idea is language is, it's the whole sort of world
of conversation that exists within a culture.
OK, if that makes sense.
and then speeches, you know.
what one person is saying. And so she was asking whether this sense of the word of the Lord of the
Word of God if it fits into one of those two categories. Right? If I'm understanding correctly and
forgive me Olga if I'm getting this wrong, but that's my understanding after having looked
this up. So what do you think about that father? Does that schema work for this?
Well, it doesn't fit neatly into...
either category, right? Because of course the ancient world, they didn't have those terms,
they didn't speak French. But I think we're going to see as we go through here in the first half,
we're going to talk about this at a more sort of conceptual level and sort of a history of
interpretation level, that of the two, it is closer to long to the first category.
My English. Yeah. Yeah.
closer, but it doesn't neatly fit there because I think there's a little bit more going on
than just the linguistic level as we're going to see.
So yeah, let's get into that.
Right, so one of the problems is that we've inherited from our...
aforementioned New England, Puritan beginnings, at least in American Christianity. The tendency
to use the phrase word of God and even word of the Lord sometimes, but more commonly word
of God to refer to the Bible.
The word of God. Yeah.
Pronounced exactly like that. Yeah. And I'm going to say that has an O within apostrophe
in it. Weird. Oh, got like like.
like Jackal enter.
Yeah, play O fish and tamo shanter.
But so obviously, you know, people are free to invent technical terms and use them
however they like, right?
We can't be the as much as you'd like to.
We can't be the word police, right?
But I would like to believe me.
but we
We do have to point out that in the Bible, the phrase word of God or word of the Lord is
never used to refer to the Bible.
Yeah, and that's really what we're focusing on is how does the Bible use this language?
Right.
Because it's the biblical use of it that's going to be then picked up by the church fathers
and picked up by later Christian tradition.
And that's not to say that there's not some sense
in which that could apply to the Bible.
But it is to say if when you think of the word of God
what comes into your brain is the Bible,
you're going to end up misinterpreting a bunch of things.
Right.
When you see that phrase in the Bible.
And in fact, the Bible doesn't call itself
anything in the Bible, really,
because the Bible doesn't talk about the Bible.
Yeah, it's not a singular book the way that we have it now.
Yeah.
Right.
out itself as sort of this co-he-
of unit, right? What you do have our references to scriptures to fit written things literally.
And so you will have texts in the scriptures, which are written later, referring to things
written earlier as scriptures, as things written.
Right. Now, does I know that that happens in the New Testament, often referring to the
Old Testament as the Scriptures. I can't recall. Do you get that?
the Old Testament, does the Old Testament ever refer to other Old Testament texts as the
scriptures?
Well, it depends on what you mean by the Old Testament.
So, most of, if we're talking about the rabbinic and most Protestant canon, then not really,
the short Old Testament as it were.
Right because I mean you see the Torah but
It's referred to as the Torah, right?
It's its own thing, right?
It is referred to as like a unit, right?
When you get into some of what some folks would call
the Deuter-O-Canonical books or the longer canon,
or how you wanna take that,
you see the earlier books refer to in various ways, right?
as the oracles of God or as things written.
And that is picked up then in the texts that make up the New Testament because every text
that is in the New Testament is a piece of second-temple Jewish literature technically.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So, yeah, so that is kind of picked up there.
That starts before that.
But the particular reason for that reference, why the things written down is a meaningful
statement, right?
That's not it.
meaningful statement for us today. We jot down notes, grocery lists, you know, reminders,
post-it notes, right? So just the fact that somebody wrote something somewhere is kind
of meaningless now. But at this time in history, remember, this is an incredibly expensive
process. This is a process that requires skills that the vast majority of the people in
the world do not have.
And I think that probably if there is a modern equivalent, maybe our phrase set in stone.
might be the closer, you know, the only
reference that we would use, like, you know, the sense of like,
okay, that's going to be a very expensive long term proposition,
actually, carve this text in stone, you know, that it's so important
and huge that we're going to go ahead and make a monument, right?
Right. Yeah, and it was, you know, when we were talking about this
during our briefing for this episode, the thing that occurred to me was,
So back in the before times.
when I was an undergrad, I actually took a course in Hindu traditions, not because I was
ever interested in becoming a Hindu. I was just, you know, interested in world religions.
But I remember the professor, and maybe I'm misremembering this, or maybe he got
wrong, I don't know. But the professor is saying at one point that the Hindu scriptures,
their tradition actually functions almost exactly the opposite way, that in their ancient
period just about the only thing that you find
written down is like really inconsequential things
that you might be liable to forget,
like a grocery list or whatever,
and that the reason why they did it that way
is because they spent a massive amount of time
committing their sacred stories to memory
and they were passed on orally all this time.
But it's interesting that within the world
that the Jewish and Christian scriptures arise,
that it's exactly the-
It was so expensive and took so much work to put a text down.
You would only put down something really important in on paper or parchment or whatever.
I imagine they probably had, they must have had some ways to jot down notes.
Was that mostly done with a wax stylist or something like that?
Well, most people weren't literate at all, but you would make little notations and some
like numbers, that kind of thing was done on pottery shards.
No, okay.
which were everywhere, Astrocca, you know, they're the...
Yeah.
Yeah, scratch paper of the ancient world.
Yeah, basically, yeah, basically the internet of its day, you know,
the, yeah.
But, uh, the garbage you would write on it.
Yeah. Right.
Right.
And it's not only the writing, right?
But it's the, then the preserve it, the copying and the preserving.
Yeah.
Right over time, uh, protection from the elements and, you know,
and, and continuing to copy and recoppy these things, which was also an expensive
and, here, process.
So.
As you said, essentially, these taxs from the Asia world were literary monuments.
And so they were treated as such.
So the fact that something had been written down and preserved this means it's significant.
So when you say it is written, right, or is it not written, right, that that gives it
this weight, not only of the initial investment in writing it down, but also that weight of
tradition of it having been now handed down to us, right, has something that was
probably important from our forebears.
And yeah, and so we've probably said on the show before,
but it probably bears repeating in this context to give people an idea.
In the first century, to get a copy of something the size of the book of Romans,
just the book of Romans, which is 16 chapters, not that long, you could read it one sitting.
A copy of that would have cost the equivalent of $5,000 in the ancient world.
So that gives you an idea, right? You didn't go and put something down like that and people didn't pay to have copies made for just junk for fanfic and, you know, like random random stuff. And so
yeah, the corollary of this, of course, is that if the expense and cost and time and effort required gave these things this great value, it means that things posted on the internet, which are
are cheap as free.
and require almost no thought or effort have no value whatsoever.
Yeah. And I just looked this up just for fun.
So the book of Romans in most English translations is about a little over 7,000 words long,
which I mean, that's if you're writing a 7,000 word paper in college,
that's about what 15, 20 pages?
23 pages. Maybe. Yeah.
Yeah, so that would take...
a month to copy down well and to have it committed to, you know, I mean just to think about that like, you know,
I can sit down and write 7,000 words probably in a couple days if I really know what I'm doing.
But then the work, you know, it's just it's really astonishing to think about the work required to do.
Right, you don't have to make your own paper.
Yeah, I don't have to make my own paper. I don't have to have good handwriting.
you know I don't have to set it down really precisely so that it's exact and you know
right? And and this is usually with ink or something like that. So we're racing it would
not be easy. You don't have to make your own ink. Yeah. Right. We don't think about that.
Right? Like the the Dead Sea Scrolls, a lot of them are if it's parchment, that's beaten
out reads if it's a vellum, that's an animal skin. Yeah. Yeah. That's been cleaned. And the
advantage of an animal skin is you could kind of erase because you could scrape it. Now you
You can only do that so much.
Right.
But you can usually take off.
a layer and and right over it. We have things that were copied over repeatedly that way.
Yep. And then the Dead Sea Scrolls, they made their ink using the soot from the oil lamps that they use.
Wow.
They would get you to know. Yeah, then you'd have to sharpen a stylus, right?
And then you'd have to, and you could only work while there was bright enough daylight for you to see,
really, because trying to do that by candlelight was almost impossible to make a copy.
Yeah, and looking like I've spent a little bit of time looking.
it the bail-off manuscript. And we're not doing our reading in the class from the manuscript,
but occasionally we are looking at pages of manuscript. And it's not the easiest thing in the world
to read or to copy, you know. And there's errors. We find scribal errors all over it.
So it's a really, it's a very high level of qualification in order to be able to make
a book in the ancient world. It's not just about banging something out. That's a few
thousand words and then
sending it to your printer, boom.
Yeah, so yes, thus scriptures,
it has all this weight behind it.
Yeah, yeah.
And so that's probably the most common wayward of God is used.
Now some modern, mostly Protestant,
though there's some Roman Catholic theology
that goes down this kind of road,
this general kind of road also,
that wants to kind of separate the concept
the Word of God, because it's very clear that, again, in the Scriptures, the concept of the Word
of God goes beyond the written Word, to say the least. Oh, yeah, sure. Yes. And so there's been an
effort to kind of acknowledge that and separate it, but this has taken kind of a weird form,
largely initiated by our 19th century German friends.
who did this by and this is one particular paradigm, but I think it illustrates kind of what they're doing.
The idea that within the written text is found in some way the word of God, but that's like a kernel.
And then the written word itself is like a husk.
And so there is then some process by which sort of the word of God is extract
or revealed or brought out or cleared from the written text. Right. So that may be a particular interpretive process. Sometimes that's a spiritual interpretive process where it's like the Holy Spirit and lightens the mind.
the mind and so you can extract the actual word of God from the written text. That can be a much more
material and mundane process.
like you follow this particular exegetical method, this particular interpretive method,
and this gives you the real word of God and gets rid of the rest. If your Carl Barth
this is preaching when the text is sort of preached and proclaimed, it becomes the word
of God in some sense to the hearers.
Why that almost sounds like the sort of Calvinist theory.
you the Eucharist, at least my understanding of it.
Well, that's because Carl Bart was a Calvin.
There you are.
Good night everybody.
Yeah.
That's how about that.
So there are, so there are those kind of theories, right?
But the problem with those theories too is that it's looking at the word of God in terms
of some kind of discursive mask.
right? It's still a text whether you identify it with the text of Scripture, with a preached text,
with a heard text, with a reality or an idea that comes into being in the brain or the mind or
before the news of the person who is reading and studying. In all of those cases you're still dealing
with the Word of God in that kind of sense.
and I only language. Right. And so what we're going to see, I think, as we go
forward here tonight, it's night somewhere. It's night in Shazakstan, I bet. Yeah. That
there it doesn't just mean more than that. I mean something different than that. Yeah.
There's not just a quantitative issue, there's a...
qualitative issue here in terms of the understanding.
Yeah, okay.
So where do we go from here?
Probably the word that probably comes to most people's minds
when thinking about this.
If they know that we're not just talking about the Bible,
is the word logos, right?
I mean, this figure's huge in,
especially the first chapter of John,
which don't worry everybody,
we're gonna actually dedicate an entire half.
in this episode to the beginning of John's Gospel.
But you know, it looms large in Greek philosophy.
There's all kinds of stuff like that.
So how does logos then figure into all of this?
Right. Well, most of modern scholarship has viewed that introduction to St. John's Gospel
that we'll be talking about soon.
Soon TM.
as the sort of Locus classicus, right, for discussing logos in this sense, the word of God, right, the logos, the who, right.
And as you might expect us to think, because this has been dominated by 19th century Germans, they've kind of gone down a wrong road in doing that.
doing that.
right? Not wrong in seeing that as the Locust Classic. It's not going to the wrong road in terms of
seeing that chapter is very important. That's why we're going to come back to it. But a wrong road in
terms of how they approach that passage and then once they've approached that passage that way,
the way they then read their conclusions into all kinds of other things.
And so methodology in most cases determines
your results. Right? Right. Yep. So, um, and in this case, the primary way that they've
approached is, as you mentioned, from this kind of philosophical background. Uh, so coming
out of central European critical studies, I'll try to lay off them a little, uh, at least
blame some French people too. Um, well, we started out this time with the French. Yeah.
Um, so
They say,
John's gospel and the Johanine literature in general in the New Testament was seen as being
very Greek.
Now you may say, well, it's written in Greek.
And Greeked.
You know, like it's hell-ellenized.
Yeah.
Right.
And this is part of a paradigm that comes out of, it's not a coincidence that the parts
of Europe that produces is actually...
more Germany than France and why it's more Germany than France or Italy is that this is really coming out
of early modern Protestant theological movements. This distinction gets made between what is
hebraic or Semitic on one hand and what is Greek or Hellenic or Hellenistic on the other.
Yeah, and I think that the reason that that comes into play is because in the
the Reformation.
there's this desire to try to scrape away all of the layers that Rome supposedly had accumulated
on top of the pure gospel. And so, you know, you can even see this, for instance, the way that
Martin Luther approaches putting together his own Bible in German, right, where he favors for
the Old Testament texts that he can only find in Hebrew and disfavours ones that are only an
extra in Greek. You know, and so there's this idea that the pure pristine gospel
is a sort of a Jewish thing.
And then the reason that Rome stacks all this stuff on top
is because of a Hellenizing, paganizing even impetus.
And so then what that does is it gives you
a very neat project, or at least it seems,
to be a very neat project,
of dumping backwards in time and saying,
okay, we can just sort of ignore the church fathers,
Although to be fair.
A number of the earliest reformers had great respect for the church fathers and quoted them and so forth.
But that it's not really necessary to be, you know, they're not really authoritative.
Let's just jump back to what's before that and we can find the pure, pristine,
Christian faith, and we don't have to worry about any of this sort of Hellenizing stuff.
But as you mentioned, of course, that narrative then gets picked up and even turned against the New Testament itself.
Right, you know now okay
even the New Testament is now suspect because it's it also is Hellenized and and look
well look there's a logos right there at the beginning of John's gospel see what he's doing right and
and as an Orthodox Christian obviously I agree that there were plenty of barnacles on the 16th century Roman Catholic Church
yes for sure but when you start scraping the barnacles you have to stop at a certain point or you'll put holes in the hole in
and sink the ship.
Right.
And I mean, this really even starts...
during the Reformation proper, right? You had people like Susinus, you had people who
start saying, we know this whole doctrine of the Trinity things sure looks Greek to me.
Oh yes, right. Right. And so, the Dytrinitarian writers, thank God they really prevail very much,
but they're there for sure. They did. They're still around. You're still folks around.
Oh yeah. And make that same argument. This is just this Greek terminology that's not in the Bible.
and you know, it's just philosophical stuff.
we need to get back to more Jewish stuff.
So yeah, and as you said, that then gets focused in on the New Testament itself, and the
Johanian literature becomes very much their focus in saying this is they start saying it's
much later than the rest of the New Testament that the early layer of the church is very
Hebrew and very Jewish.
stuff like the synoptic gospels as opposed to St. John's gospel.
and Saint Paul's epistles as opposed to the general epistles, right?
And so this gets stratified and
it gets to the point where in the early 20th century, our German friends are just straight out saying that they think Saint John's Gospel
and these kind of things are gnostic or proto-nostic or you know, but essentially they're tending in the direction of gnosticism because it is
Hellenized.
over against Jewish.
Yeah.
So that means that as they approach, for example,
John chapter one and say,
what does Saint John mean by logos,
by logos that who, by the word of God, right?
What does he mean?
They go straight to Greek philosophy.
Yeah.
Right.
Do not pass the Old Testament,
do not collect $200.
Right?
the first place where you really see
a kind of important philosophical use of logos that really sets the tone for probably
the most common way we still use words derived from the Greek word logos today is in Heraclitus
who uses logos to refer in two ways first to refer to ordered structures out in the world
in nature in the cosmos. There are these ordered structures out there and then because there
Where are these ordered structures?
out there in the world, we can then have an ordered account and discourse about those
objects in the world.
Yeah, because there's a logos out there then we can express a logos of that stuff which
is then why you have all of these English words that end with ology.
You know, it's the idea is this is the human logos about this logos that we can observe,
you know, and, and I mean, people will often gloss that suffix of sorts to mean, it means
of but it doesn't quite mean that actually it's broader than that. It's this idea like you said
of an order to count a whole discourse about that particular subject, whatever it is.
Right which of course then obviously has to presuppose that there is some order out there to be
described in an orderly fashion. Yeah. Because if it's just chaos out there then you can't give an
order to count of it sort of by definition, right? So, like, no. Life on Earth, right?
Okay.
has an order to it so we can study
biologos, right? The biology, right?
And ontology, right? Being is
ordered so we could have ontology, right?
And on and on and on and on.
So that's kind of an
or layer of this that lies behind
later philosophically uses. None of
the later philosophical uses are going to deny that.
They're all going to nuance that or add to that.
build upon that. One of the most influential comes in stoicism. The major change stoicism
makes when they talk about the logos is that the stoics see the logos as an active force,
not just as they sort of inert order, right, or just a structure, but as a sort of active
the course.
In order, we'll talk about this.
Yeah, they talk about a spermaticos logos
That is seed in the sense that the logos brings
Life from lifelessness. It's like this organized positive organizing principle like a world soul or a demi urge
That's in everything and that is actively
Working and producing things that includes in people and so there is this sort of element of the divine
that's in everyone and every.
thing within, within stoicism, and that is actively doing something. Right. Right. So then on
this journey to get to St. John, right. You, you inevitably stop in a phylo of Alexandria or phylo
Alexander Elegs and Drinas, if you want to be a fan.
Who is usually the gloss of who he is,
is he's a quote unquote Hellenistic Jew.
Right, that's the way he's usually describes.
Yeah.
because he lived in Alexandria, Egypt, who is part of the Egyptian Jewish community. Obviously,
Alexandria and Egypt was a center of great philosophical and general learning. He's writing
in Greek. He's interacting with philosophical sources and philosophical ideas.
And so the typical read of him taken by these scholars has been that he's just what they call
middle plateness. Right, it's both...
to like a classical platenist or a neoplatenist. He's a middle platenist. He's somewhere in between.
And that he basically Hellenized Judaism. That he sort of took Judaism, pre-existing Judaism,
and put it through the sausage machine. And that grid grounded up to fit into Greek philosophical
categories. And so it's kind of this this melding but then it's not really true.
to pre-existing Judaism. Yeah, and that's a hellenizing of Judaism. Right. And so this relates
to something we've talked about a lot, this tendency for the people of any era, but especially
in the modern era, to just assume that Old Testament Judaism is exactly like rabbinic Judaism.
Right right and so you hold up phylo and you hold up rabbinic Judaism and they don't look a lot all
right? What he writes looks more like Greek literature that it looks like
rabbinic Judaism therefore see exhibit A right and there are a number of
individual sort of topics within that like they'll point out like oh see
phylo thinks that you have to have these intermediary beings between God and
creation because God can't lower himself to creation see that's really
platonic that's almost nostec and etc etc. So we are going to
here in a little bit, get, come back to Filo and talk about a different way to read him.
Right. Right. And so, so here's the kicker is that, you know, when, when the Dead Sea Scrolls
were dug up, which of course we've referred to lots of times on this show. And they have all
these texts in them from the Second Temple Jewish period. It's actually shown that Filo is
pretty much an alignment with them.
And in fact, he's actually super Jewish and not Hellenizing it at all.
And you know that there's this and that this trove of second-time Jewish literature that
are found in the Dead Sea Scrolls shows that actually there isn't a Greek influence.
And in fact, often abominates Hellenism entirely.
Like it's it's very deliberately kind of against it.
So if you compare that against Filo, then you actually get a really different image.
and
and a really different image of the gospel of John as well.
Right, because, so when we talk about the Dead Sea Scrolls,
there's two categories of Dead Sea Scrolls.
One of them is copies of texts that we have elsewhere.
So they have texts of most of the books of the Old Testament.
They have texts that are in some people's Old Testament,
and not other people's Old Testament.
They have a lot of copies of Inak and Jubilee.
and some other texts like that that we have other places.
There are also what are called the sectarian documents
or the sectarian texts.
What does that mean?
Why are they called the sectarian?
They're called that because these are specific to
the community at Kumaran that produced the Dead Sea Scrolls.
Okay, so they're not found anywhere else.
Right, so it's like if you went through all my books
and papers, you would find copies of a lot of books,
that other people have copies of, right?
You would that might all-
find the bound copy of my dissertation that other people don't necessarily have.
You'd also find just a lot of papers of mine, like old school papers, seminar papers,
PhD papers, they weren't published anywhere, that are just mine.
And you would find, you know, signed documents and things that were particular to me and my house
and all that. So the sectarian documents are all those things that are particular to that community,
into their way of life and their organization and yeah so and that kind
We can refer to your dissertation as your sectarian text then.
Yes, yes. It is a de-young sectarian document.
And apocryphal because it is hidden.
So when we look at those sectarian texts, that gives us an idea of the particular things about
that community. The other text give us an idea about more general shape.
Judaism, right on a whole. But you can't take the sectarian text and say, oh, we'll see Jews
everywhere believed XYZ because it's here in this text that we only found at Kumaran, right?
You have to just say, well, we know they thought it wasn't. Yeah, right, right.
So when you look at particularly those sectarian texts, you find a lot of the themes that are in
Saint John's Gospel and in his epistles.
and even the book of Revelation.
And specifically, you find a lot of the themes
that people were pointing to to try and say
he was Greek and borderline, Nostek, right?
So this, like a lot of dualisms between light
and darkness and children of light
and children of darkness and those who are of God
and those who are of the devil,
those were all thought to be olic dualism, Plato, Ah, see?
Ah.
But it turns out that was very common
very common.
second-term Jewish way of seeing things, like insiders to the community outside of the
hostile world outside, that this was not uncommon.
And so now not only has the whole, this is the least Jewish literature in the New Testament
thing been to bunked.
Now there are a lot of scholars arguing that the Johanian literature is some of the most
Jewish, some of the most deeply immersed in Second Temple Jewish thought.
In terms of the thought life, right, and the worship life as opposed to, it's not that St.
Matthew's gospel isn't Jewish somehow, but, but in terms of reflecting that kind of theological
and liturgical thought, you find actually more of that in the Johanning literature than
in a lot of the other literature.
Well, so that means if we're going to say that, okay, fair enough for us is
Christians, chapter one of St. John's Gospel,
Locust Classicas for what logos that,
what the word of God is,
then we have to come to it not by way
of Greek philosophical traditions
but by way of Hebrew and Jewish traditions.
Right, so we have to start in the Old Testament.
All right.
We said all that to say this.
Right, well, you know,
There are a lot of things to-
you'd think should go without saying, right? Like if you want to say the New Testament,
start with the Old Testament, but that's a big fight.
Yeah, I mean, you know, I was, it's colorless. I was raised with this idea about St. John's
gospel, not to impune it, right? But just simply to say, Oh, well, St. John is using these
preexisting Greek philosophical concepts in order to, you know, begin sort of talking to
the nation. So it was, I think the way that it was, it was usually described to me. You
that he deliberately use is using
Greek logos philosophy to make his case. So I mean, there is a kind of conservative version,
right, of all of that. Right. This isn't just all whack jobs. Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. But I think a lot of it just comes from, like you said, there's this assumption
that comes as a result of the concerns of the Reformation and then it just sort of cascades from
there in a lot of different ways. Right. Yeah. Right. It establishes a parrot.
time and that paradigm then gets applied in ways that the people who came up with that
paradigm didn't necessarily intend. Some of them they would have been appalled by, but
it sort of takes it. What's you let something lucid to the world? It takes its own course,
right?
Yeah, and I'll just say before we get into what we're really going to talk about in this
episode, for those who are interested in maybe looking at this question in the other
direction temporarily, like okay what does it look like for this?
Christianity and classical culture, what you know, to interact, what does it look like after the New Testament stuff?
There is a great book that has exactly that title, Christianity and classical culture by Yaroslav Pelican.
And he shows, frankly, how what happens is instead of the church being Hellenized,
Hellenism became Christianized is what actually occurred.
Is it that the influence went the other way that it transformed classical culture by virtue of its contact
with Christian.
So just to put a plug out there for a book by a guy who really does know what he's talking about and you know my god my god rest his soul.
Right and yeah, and that's why we're going to spend the time we're about to spend on phylo for example.
Yeah.
Is to understand that because this paradigm isn't just applied to like phylo, you know,
unless you're at least a little bit of a Bible nerd you've probably never heard of him.
Right? Yeah.
He's not a church father, he's not a saint, right?
You know, like rehabilitating him is...
not crucial, but the paradigm and the judgment and the way of reading that's applied to him
is also applied by the same people to the church fathers.
Right.
Exactly.
And there it becomes important, right?
Because you're talking about undermining sort of fundamental Christian doctrines, right?
Which are no longer seen by some of our friends as fundamental Christian doctrines because
they're now, quote unquote, Greek.
Yeah.
They come in later.
So, but before.
all that, before all of that, way, way deep into the Old Testament, you have this phrase
exists in Hebrew. So what is it in Hebrew? So you have this, Debar Yahweh, right, which Yahweh,
obviously, is the name of the God of Israel. And then, working for that as Debar, which is usually
translated as word and so that phrase is usually
you'll see it in your
English Bibles, it's not really translating it, but you'll see in your English Bibles as the word of the Lord.
Yeah, or Lord in all caps. Yeah, or sometimes word of God and then God in all caps, because they're trying to communicate Yahweh with that.
Right. And so this is very similar to what we talked about last time when we talked about the angel of the Lord. Right.
right? Where it was Malak Yahweh, right? We have the two words sort of
set next to each other, right? And then they relate to each other. And the word of is put in
there in English, sort of, to punt, right? In terms of the relationship between the two.
But so we have to start in this case with the bar, right? And what that means, it can be translated word.
Okay. Right. But it has a very broad range of meaning. So if you go and decide, I'm going to
learn biblical Hebrew today and you go and you buy a
set of biblical Hebrew flashcards. The flashcard for debar will say on the back word comma matter comma
thing. Yeah, which is which is even broader than the Greek concept of logos. Right. So that's
wide open. And so but it's you can tell from and matter there is not matter like material. It's
matter like a matter, a matter of discussion, right?
A matter for issue or a question.
Right, right. And so this is word kind of in the sense of concept.
Right. Like, and it's thing the way we would say that's not a thing.
Or yeah, that is a thing. Right. Like it's it's it's it's not it's definitely not limited to a written
word or even a spoken word. Right. It goes sort of beyond that. Okay. Right.
So, but it is the kind of thing that
It would be communicated in language.
It is something that would be communicated, and language would be one way to communicate
it, I should say.
We've talked about others' music, or ritual, but it's what would be behind that.
If you talk about the sign and the thing signified, this would be the thing signified.
Yeah, right.
Right?
The referent, as it were.
Right.
And so when you put that just like as we talked about with the angel of the Lord,
when you put the two words together, there is a way in which that could be taken in a possessive sense,
like Yahweh's word. And that's borne out. There are places in the Old Testament where the God of Israel refers to my word.
Yeah, and and and that's where you kind of get some space then for the English use of where which we are
often used to refer to something as possessive or genitive.
Right.
But there are also other English way, C-sort of,
and as we talked about last time, like fistful of dollars.
The, and one way is that it's kind of agic-tival.
Right. So like another example from the scriptures.
If we say the crown of...
glory. Right? That's not a crown that's made of glory. Right?
Glory is at the substance that makes it up. And it's not a crown that belongs to
glory. Right? It's a glorious crown. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's being used like an
adjective. Right? And so just like we talked about with the angel of the Lord,
another way of reading this is it we said, that could just be the Yahweh angel.
Right, this could be the Yahweh word.
Hmm.
Right.
And that's another way to understand.
And that gets at, as we're going to see, a way in which this is referred to in a personal
sense.
In the same way that sort of the Yahweh angel sort of is Yahweh, we're going to see that
the word of Yahweh sort of is Yahweh.
Now sometimes in the Hebrew they will use the word Rima instead of...
Debar and this is a place where I'm gonna have to reemphasize. I know how mad
people got when I talked about the different words for love. They always do what
I bring that up. But synonyms are a thing. Yes, there are synonyms in the Bible.
Synonyms are Debarim. Oh, yes, see what I did there. Nice. Yeah, because I know, I know
you know, much is made of this by especially our friends in the work.
faith, penicostal movement, where they literally, like it's, you know,
Rayma Bible College, right? Or, you know, the Rayma Institute, and you know,
it's Rema really. Well, if you're pronouncing it with modern Greek pronunciation,
you know, this idea that it's the spoken word versus the more kind of conceptual word, but
actual biblical usage pretty much makes them synonyms, right? Debar and Rema?
Yeah.
I mean, Rima, the Greek term.
Logos, Rima, excuse me, a logos, Rima.
Yeah.
And so yeah, they're just sitting in them sometimes.
Sometimes there's not a reason.
It's just a particular author's preference
or that kind of thing.
To prove that they're a technical term,
you have to demonstrate that each term is only used
consistently one way in a given writer.
Yeah.
Right.
And then you can prove that.
Now again, a modern person.
is perfectly fine to make theological distinctions and label them with Greek words.
Yes, right. But they shouldn't say that that's the way the Bible uses those words.
Right. Because then the problem is people go back and read those distinctions back into the Bible.
Right. Yep. Right. And that gives you a false sense. So yeah. And one of the proofs that,
you know, that these words are interchangeable, that they are synonyms is the way that it gets
it's worked out in trin-
translations, which, you know, what is a translation? A translation is on some level in interpretation
because it shows you what the understanding of the translator is when he translates a particular
word. One of the examples that I ran across actually while studying Old English is, so Alvara
who was an abbot in England that did a lot of translations of religious texts, he was translating
Genesis chapter 3 from the Volga.
from the Latin Vulgate into Old English.
And I can't remember if I've mentioned this
on this podcast before, I don't think so.
But he, you know, when the serpent is speaking to Eve
and he says to her, you know, don't you know you'll be as gods,
that's the word that's used in the Latin, right?
That it's the word for gods.
Whereas when Alvaryk translated it,
he has the serpent say, don't you know you'll be as angels?
Which it's interesting because Old English does have word for gods.
I mean
It's basically God, by the way.
Good, you know.
But he translates as angels, which shows what his understanding
of what's being talked about there is.
And so that's an example of the way that translation lets you know
what the understanding of the translator is.
And so that's why you can then use translations as a way
to kind of triangulate backwards to see how these texts are
received in particular communities
and what the understanding of them is.
Right. Right. Yeah.
and end.
And yeah, all translations require interpretation.
Yeah, I mean, there's no such thing as a neutral translation.
There's no way around it.
Yeah.
Words in one language do not equal words in another language.
Even if they're related etymologically, they still aren't equal.
Yeah.
Even if the languages are closely related, it's just still, yeah.
Right.
Yep.
So with that in mind, right, what happens?
This is going to be sort of an object case, and then we're going to sort of put this into
practice with the rest of the Bible and the other two halves of the program.
What if we approach Filo and the things that Filo says about the logos from the perspective
of the Old Testament, from the perspective of Second Temple Judaism, rather than from the
perspective of Greek philosophy?
And this discussion is going to owe a lot to Daniel Boyar and's reappraisal of Filo.
boy R&N is a an Orthodox Jewish scholar.
of Second Temple Judaism, including teaching on the New Testament. He sees it as
firmly within Second Temple Judaism and so he approaches it from that way too. But
he has done sort of a major re-evaluation of Philo as an important part for
him of his Jewish tradition and wanting to show how he actually brought Jewish
ideas in
middle plateenism rather than vice versa. And so yeah, so he wants to see
phyllo as Judy-Eising Hellenism, not Hellenizing Judaism.
Yeah, which as we mentioned that Pelican book shows the church father is doing
basically exactly that, Christianizing Hellenism, not Hellenizing Christianity. So I mean in that
And that way, in that way, phyllo is kind of functioning in a sort of pre-petristic way.
right. He's doing this a similar kind of thing. Yeah. Yeah. He's trying to explain Judaism to Greeks the way the
father, the early fathers would be explaining Christianity to Greeks. And also just to be
Judaism, Judaism and Hellenizing Judaism. I know that sounds a lot alike. Right? That sounds like we
were just playing a word game. Right? You got your Peter Butter in my chocolate. You got your chocolate in my
peanut butter, let's try it.
But the key here is which of the two is controlling.
That's what we're talking about.
We're talking about which is the master
which is a servant in this relationship, right?
Is it for a follow, is it Judaism that's in charge?
And he's using Greek ideas in service of that?
Or is he using Greek as he appealing to Greek ideas
and using Jewish language in service of that?
and the same thing.
then with the Church Fathers and Christianity. Are they Christians who are using Greek language
and Greek ideas to serve the explanation of the Christian faith? Or are they, as they've been
accused? Are they basically just Greek amateur philosophers throwing in some Christian language
here and there? Right? Just kind of in service of their Greek ideas. Right. And you can tell that
our position. It's that for Philo's Judaism.
charge and for the church fathers and Christianity that's in charge and and Hellenism is being made
put in service of those things. Yes, just like translations, I am not neutral.
That I make no pretense to neutrality on this or anything else. Right? So,
but looking at some of these same ideas, right, that were used to say that Philo is basically a
plate nest primarily. If we approach those from the perspective of the T2.
of the Old Testament and the second temple ideas. So let's say we approach this impurity
of the material world where he talks about God having these intermediaries between himself
and the material creation. Well, we've talked about that in past episodes. This is the tower
of Babel. Because of the whole death by holiness problem that produces the tabernacle
the Torah, the angelic princes of the nations, all of that is because for God to be close
to sinful humanity, it's not that the material world is corrupt in and of itself by virtue
of being material, but it has been corrupted. Yeah, right. And so God's holiness is destructive. He
has to step back and have these intermediaries out of love for his creation. Yeah, it's the death by
by holiness. Yeah, yeah, that's what's going on. Yeah.
And so it's very clear when you read Filo
from this perspective that Filo is talking about
the logos as sort of the supreme mediator
between the two, because he's the one
who sort of presides in the divine council.
He's the one who among all of these beings,
these angelic beings, who Filo is not shy
about calling gods, plural.
Right.
but he is sort of supremum.
among them, right? And sort of the the the commander of them and immediate God to
creations. And these intermediaries are not like
Gnostic emanations from God. They're not so there's not sort of this scale of being with
God at the top and matter at the bottom. And they're somewhere in between on these
different levels. These are, follow is very clear, these are created
beings. These are created gods who are not worshiped their own right.
created by God in a signed sort of administrative duties.
Right. Yep.
The divine counts.
Yeah.
Right. And you know, you look at a sort of a subset of this is that he sees
the logos as being the the lowest the word as being the instrument through
which God creates the creation. Right.
again, you could take that in this sort of
the platonic way, the way that later Nostics did,
because Plato's Tameas was found, for example,
amid the Nagamadi texts, just mixed in with the Nostics texts.
In Plato's Tameas, there is, because the good, right,
being itself can't know lesser things, right?
It's sort of naturally detached from everything else that exists.
It's only itself.
Right, there's there's this lesser being
the Demi-erge, who sort of loves the good
and so fashions things sort of as best it can after.
The good, right?
And so if you approach Filo from that direction,
you could say, oh, see the logos is like the Demi-erge,
right? It's this lesser thing that creates, right?
But if we approach this from a perspective of the Old Testament,
you crack open Genesis 1, right?
right from the beginning God creates by speaking.
the word, right?
Yep.
That's the instrument through which he creates is the word in Genesis.
It's got nothing to do with anything of the Tamaas, right?
Now, now, would Philo, if he was talking to a Platonist, would Philo have pointed to
that and drawn some connection to try to help the Platonist understand what he was saying
about Genesis, probably.
Right.
doesn't mean that
that he means the same thing.
Yeah, you could say, look, look, look, pal,
it's like the Demi-Eurage,
but here's some important ways in which that is not true as well.
Again, you know, like one of the distinctions
that you like to draw a lot,
there's continuities and there's discontinuities.
And there's discontinuities are very important.
Right, right.
And so he not only has the logos there at the beginning
of the creation wherever creating is putting things
in order.
Right? And it's not only that he puts things in order, but for Filo, the logos continues
to be present and keep things in that order. And you can compare to that Colossians 1 verse 17.
Yes. Right. So Colossians 1, 17 saying about Christ, and he is before all things and in him,
all things hold together. Right. So that same kind of idea. Right.
Yeah.
coming from St. Paul. And so one of the key discontinuities as you were just mentioning,
between some of these other views is that, uh, phylo clearly holds that the logos is a person.
Yeah, not a personal being. Yeah, not a kind of emanation or, I mean, that's probably the most
obvious thing. But, you know, or a power or force. Yeah. Like the like the logos in in stoicism,
right where it's the sort of fourth.
Yeah. Yeah. Um, 10 power, but it seems it is a person with an identity. Yeah. One, you know,
one of the powers in heaven, right? One of the two powers in heaven. One of the, you know,
yeah, yep, yep. Right. And uh, Philo goes so far at one point to refer to the logos as the
first born of God. Now don't get too excited. Right. I was about to get excited, but then I
I remember the notes.
Yeah. Right. This, you know, oh, wait, we got
pita terin is a bit least here, right? And
phyllo actually has three. He actually has
the concept of the spirit too. But ultimately,
when you get into the details, phyllo was
basically what we would later call a semi
area. Yeah. He believed that the the logos
and the spirits sort of came into being, but
they were
produced from God's own essence.
Yeah, so there are kind of creations on some level.
Right, but they're not made of other stuff.
Yeah, right, right.
Yeah.
And I mean, it's important, you know, we talk about Filo,
and we, you know, mentioned, you know, up to this point,
pretty much we would agree with almost all these things
he says, we're not claiming him as some kind of shadow church
father or whatever.
Right.
He's not a Christian.
he does not have the gospel presented to
him, but it's interesting how much he gets right. Yeah. Yeah. Well, because what he's reflecting is,
he's reflecting in Greek, right? Sort of the pre-existing ideas of second temple Judaism.
Right. Yeah, the stuff is in the end. Yeah. And the apostles are going to take this because the
apostles are worshipping the same way, believing the same things, reading the same texts, but they're
They're going to encounter the person of Jesus Christ.
that's gonna let them connect the dots, right?
That's gonna let them make the big important connection
here.
And just as a callback to our last episode,
Philo also identifies the logos as the angel of the Lord.
How about that?
So he says, when De Barrio, or Malacio,
where show up in the Old Testament, it's the same person.
It's the same person, the same second power in heaven,
kind of idea.
that he talked about before.
And so lastly.
Yeah, and this is right before we get our first break.
We're going to shift away from Alexandria and head back down into Palestine.
Yeah, and it's in Fireins.
Yes, and they're about.
Yeah, and that's two.
We have some fun with Air May, I can briefly.
Yeah.
And that's in what are called the Targums.
Targums are at...
they're usually referred to as Aramaic translations
of the Hebrew scriptures.
Right, but they're not exactly.
And the reason, yeah, so what are they?
So, you know, by the first century, okay.
People in Palestine and Israel don't speak Hebrew, right?
It's just a liturgical language by this point.
And only those who are really educated in that
actually will be able to speak.
it. And so what they would do is if you'd go to the synagogue, the scripture would be read
in Hebrew by someone who could read out loud in Hebrew. And then there would be a Targam
recited, which is essentially a summary of the Hebrew text, but in Aramaic. So the idea,
so you know, if you went there, since if you were a local, you know, you would speak Aramaic or maybe
Greek also.
And you would hear it read in Hebrew, you wouldn't know what it said.
And then someone would read this Targam that would basically said, okay,
what he just said was.
And then he would read off the summary and then you would be able to get that
because you would understand that in in Aramaic.
Because again, Hebrew is not a not being a spoken language in the first century.
It's already just a liturgical language by that point.
So we will now have a profound test of Father Andrews honesty.
since this is pre-recorded.
Because I am about to um...
I'll go for it. Yeah, no, I'm actually will this remain in the recorded episode or will he edit it to make it
self-correct me. That was the best understanding. Yeah. So one of those things was not quite right. Okay.
One of those things was the opposite of correct. Oh, great. So hook me up.
So the one that was not quite right was if you went to a synagogue in the first century, in particular,
You would be just as, depending on where you-
are in the world maybe more likely to only hear the scriptures read in Greek.
Oh, okay. That is true. I was thinking about the palace.
That's the not quite right part. Okay. Got it. Got it.
But even in Pals, even in Galilee, for example, they were primarily using Greek. If you
were Judea, right. So the rule was you had to, this is how highly they respected in pre-Christian
second-table Judaism. How highly they respected the Greek translations of
the Old Testament was that you could read it instead of the Hebrew in synagogues. You could
not read the Aramaic instead of the Hebrew. If you read the Aramaic, you had to also read
the Hebrew. Okay. Okay. So that's the part that wasn't quite right. Okay. So the part
that was the opposite of correct is you could say that it's okay. Instead of, well, I'm
kind of doing a play to riff there. It's subtle. Anyway.
So the the targums were actually not some reason they're actually expansions. Oh I see of the Hebrew text. Well, I wasn't as long as I was suspected for a second there that I was going to be. So they they would the text was translated into Aramaic, but then it was also expanded upon and elaborated. I see.
and different targums which are usually named based on where they were found or based on a rabbi associated with...
them. There's a bunch of different reasons. The city they were found in like an Egypt, that kind of thing.
Different targets had different philosophies. So some of them would be more like the message that we
talked about last time, where it's an expansion in the sense that it would get sort of really colloquial,
or use like four or five words to explain the meaning of one Hebrew word, right, to kind of get
at what they thought the idea was. This is why you couldn't read it instead of the Hebrew, right?
because it might give you the wrong eye.
right? They weren't necessarily endorsing what every commentator thought. But some of them were
even wilder than that. Some of them have whole stories that aren't in the Hebrew text, just insert
it like traditional stories and stuff. So you can find there's a wealth of literature from this
period just found in the Targums in these versions of stories. So they function as commentaries as well.
them. Right. Yeah. Right. And
One of the most interesting things, I'm just gonna throw this out and then do nothing with it.
So, deal with it everybody.
As you try to fight off your Turkey coma and keep listening this episode.
So, when Christ famously, from the cross says, Ellie, Ellie, Lama, Subakhtari.
Yep.
Right.
And we know he's quoting Psalm 22 because he's praying Psalm 22.
Ah.
He's praying the Targum of it.
That's air of Mayak, not Hebrew.
I knew he was doing air of Mayak.
Yeah.
So yeah, yeah.
And now I'm going to do nothing with that.
I just threw it out there.
Yep.
Do it with it what you will.
Yeah.
Well, that's not a big secret.
See, I'm actually getting OK that I wasn't actually as hard
as I suspected I was about to be.
I try to be kind.
Well, that's very nice.
I often fail, but I try.
You can brutalize me when we make the stop button.
Um, so, okay, so targums.
Yes, I, I, I withstood you to your face in anti-actual.
No.
Um, so, uh, right.
So what of one of these minor expansions of the text or commentaries on the text, right,
is that we frequently see in Targums, and this is across several different Targums.
We see that places where Yahweh, where
the Lord, the name of the God of Israel is mentioned. There will be inserted where there isn't
in the Hebrew text, Memoraw, which is the word word. Memoraw is Wormic. Right. And so it's
basically even in places where it doesn't say the word of the Lord, it just says the Lord,
this will add it. So it says word of the Lord. And this isn't haphazard. There's a pattern.
This gets added
places where God is seen by somebody where Yahweh is described as having body parts.
Where Yahweh eats with someone. Any of those things that have to do with having a body or being seen.
any of those where it isn't already present
Memorog gets added so it's the Word of the Lord.
And this is a way within this interpretation of the text.
This is a way to deal with one of the problems
we talked about last time, like an Exodus,
we're the same chapter, right?
Talk to Moses talks to Yahweh face to face,
smout them out the way a man speaks to his friend,
and then was eight or nine versus later,
you can't see me and live, right?
Right. This is one of the.
of dealing with that, right? It's making they see this pattern in some parts of the text and we're
going to go through those parts in our second half. They see this pattern in parts of the Old Testament
where there's this figure of the word of Yahweh, the word of the Lord who is seen and interacted with
and does these things. And then there's this other sense in which Yahweh can't be seen. And their
way of doing this, they say, well, we'll take this distinction that we see in some parts of the Old
and we'll just make it consistent across the whole thing.
Yeah, cool.
All right, well, with that, we're going to go ahead and go to our first break and we'll
be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Saint Ignatius, first century bishop of Antia.
called the God-bearer is one of the earliest witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature
of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child, Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as
an example of the child-like faith all Christians must possess.
In bearing God, Father Andrew Damoc recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
saint, and interprets for the modern reader five major themes in the pastoral letters
he wrote.
the church and the Eucharist.
For Ignatius martyrdom is really the fullness of Christ
in a sense, which that can be challenging for us.
Because number one, he doesn't seem to have any
reticence at all about going to martyrdom.
Like there's no sense of, well, this play have to do.
You know, I wish I didn't have to, but this is God's book for me.
He is going to it joyfully, gladly.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to
store.info.com.
book and others like it, you can go to store.
AncientFaith.com. Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a
question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Well, welcome to the second half of the show.
And normally, normally we would take your calls, like you just heard the voice of Steve
say.
But again, this is a prerecorded episode.
Hope everyone at least United States is having a great Thanksgiving for you outside the
United States.
Well, I hope you're having a very nice day wherever it is that you are.
You're really disappointed that this isn't live.
I am.
No reason for it.
Yeah.
Right.
So okay.
Well, we have another message that was left for us.
And this one is, well,
kind of wonderfully introduced what we're talking about in the second half. This one
our caller is asking about something he read in the Book of Jubilee. So here it is.
Hello, Father Andrew and Father Stephen. This is Donald from Illinois. I finally
came from downloaded an audio book version of the Book of Jubilee. And as I was
listening, my ears perked up at the following verse from the beginning of chapter 14.
From the new moon to the third month, the word of the Lord came to Abram in a
saying, if you're not Abram, I am the Defender and the reward will be...
exceeding great. It seems like an Arkham's razor reading in this passage would
suggest that the word here is just God's immaterial voice not necessarily the
second person of the Trinity. I've wondered for quite some time prior to the
gospel of John, what evidence is there that the word of the Lord is indeed the
hypostasis of God Christ? Thank you. Okay so Jubilee's chapter 14, right? It's
It's basically a rehashing of Genesis 15, isn't it?
a light remix. Yeah, there you go. This is a Targon maybe? No. Yeah. As I've just learned.
Honestly, honestly, sort of. Yeah. So there's a paper thing. Yeah. Not for me. I'm not
ready to go. Yeah. But you know, I mean, not exactly, but there's a there there. Yeah.
There's something there.
Yeah.
So yeah, and it's a sort of light remix of James.
Genesis 15 verses one through seven.
Yeah, the word of the Lord comes to Abram in a dream in Jubilee's.
And so that's the basis of Thanos question.
But then in Genesis 15, it's not a dream exactly.
It's what's the word that's used there?
It's an a vision.
Yeah, which dream vision, I mean, you know, these are often the same kind of thing.
Yeah, they're, they're, they're not totally dissimilar.
and right.
Probably the connection is based on sort of a I mean Jubilee's is written much later, right?
So we're talking in the post-exilic period
And so you have a lot in as you see in the book of Daniel right in
Babylonian thought you have a lot of dream prophecy whereas
When you're looking at that period of ancient Israel's history that would be reflected in
Genesis prophets were seers. Yeah, right who saw
you know, visions. So that that's probably the connection there is trying to get at the same idea.
Yep.
Um, and that this is a prophetic thing. Um, but yes, but so if, if, if the word of Yahweh comes to
Abram in a vision that tells you right off the bat, right, that he's seeing something.
It's visual. Yeah. So that's not, it's not as it's sometimes depicted in movies or just in our
imagination that you know the word
the Lord coming to someone means they hear a voice. Yeah, just yeah, a disembodied voice.
You know, they hear more infreement somewhere off speaking, you know, and that's it.
Oh, so this is they see someone, right? And so Abram, in this instance, in Genesis 15,
in verse two and verse two.
say he calls this person who he's seeing the Lord Yahweh, which creates kind of a problem
for English translations, at least modern English translations because they are sticking
by the rabbinic Jewish thing of not wanting to print the name Yahweh, but their general
pattern is that when they get that, they replace it with Lord in all caps.
But if they did that here.
that Abraham would be calling him the Lord Lord.
Yeah, so they translate it usually as Lord God
and then God and all caps.
Yeah, even though the word God is nowhere in the text.
Yeah, it's, it's simply says Yahweh.
Yeah, so this is, add this to the list of reasons
why we just go ahead and say it to convey what's actually there in the text.
But the important thing here is that this figure
figure who is identified in the near-
of verse one as the word of Yahweh who comes to
the division is called by Abram, Lord Yahweh, and the
figure does not correct him.
Yeah, right?
Just say, wait, wait, wait, wait, I'm just messenger.
I'm just, yeah, so this guy named Word.
So it's clear that Abram refers to the Word of the
Lord who comes to him as being Yahweh the God of Israel
and the word of the Lord does not say, no, no, no, no, don't
call me that.
You
It's true.
Yeah.
Right.
And it isn't that there's a switch of root that happens here because in verse four, after the first time Abram calls him that, he is again referred to as the word of Yahweh.
And then in verse seven, the word of Yahweh calls himself Yahweh.
Right.
And then in verse 8, Abraham again calls him Lord Yahweh.
So we see here.
a pattern with the Dabari-Awe that we already saw last time in with the angel of
Lord with the Malak-Awe that this figure, this person is both identified as Yahweh, the God of Israel,
but also distinguished by the addition of another word, right? In this case, the word word,
in the last episode the word.
angel or messenger, right? So that's sort of our exhibit A from the Old Testament. And as you
mentioned at the beginning, I know last time we went through every mention of the angel of the
Lord, at least in passing, at least briefly, we honestly can't do that. Forward of the Lord.
Yeah, it's a bunch. And word of God is there's too many. But so we're going to talk about some very
important ones and then
And after we've gone through some very significant ones,
we're going to sort of give some more general statements
about certain portions of the Old Testament
that will sort of convey the overall idea.
Yeah, and I should point out here like,
okay, so I just checked in,
I checked the ESV, I mean, mind you,
different translations could do this differently,
but I just checked the ESV.
And there are 274 instances of word of the Lord
that exists to the ESP.
Right.
And let's check word of God, 51 for word of God.
So yeah, yeah, we don't have time to do each of those.
So but we're gonna, I think cover the ground adequately
in the second half.
Yes.
If you disagree, said you're hate me,
I'll do father Andrew.
Yep, I'll take it.
Delete, delete.
Yeah.
So yeah, so the next really significant one
that we wanna look at in a little depth
is in 1 Samuel chapter 3.
Okay, and this it's the first 21 verses of that chapter and this is basically the call of Samuel to be a prophet.
So Samuel is at this point a yut.
He is young guy.
Yeah.
And he has gone to, you know, I guess because they're trying to be consistent.
There are a bunch of English trans
that say he was in this
actually he was sleeping in the temple of the Lord.
Now, this is for Samuel, David isn't even king yet.
I don't think David is even born yet,
let alone Solomon, there is no temple.
It's the house of the Lord.
It's talking about at Shiloh,
the place where the tabernacle was,
the Ark of the Covenant.
And when it says that he's sleeping in the,
quote unquote, temple of Yahweh,
where the Ark of the Covenant was,
the COVID it was. It just that
sleeping in the holy of holies on a cot. It means that the locale. He lives there. Yes.
So just to clarify that. But so he's and currently Eli is the high priest and his sons,
his near-do-well sons are serving his priests. And so now this is the point where Samuel is going
to be called to become.
a prophet and in establishing that situation in verse one of that chapter and
describing sort of the dire situation that Israel is still in because remember
we're coming out of the book of Judges so things are pretty dire.
There's still dire. We're told in that verse verse that the word of Yahweh is
rare because there are not many visions.
Yeah, which I mean that's that's an interesting way to put it
which, again, underlines that an encounter with the word of the Lord is a visual encounter.
It's an encounter with someone.
Yeah, someone that you can see.
Yeah, not with just an idea or a thought or a whisper, or that kind of thing.
thing. And we're told that in verse seven that Samuel himself did not know Yahweh.
the God of Israel because he hadn't seen the word of Yahweh. The way that's phrased,
usually in the English translation, we'll say something like the word of Yahweh had not been
revealed to him. Yeah, that's what it is in the ESB. Right. And that's kind of ambiguous as to exactly
what that means, right? Because revealed to him could be a voice, could be a printed text, could be,
right? Yeah.
But the word there in Hebrew actually means to uncover
or unveil or display something.
So I'm guessing that in the Greek Old Testament,
that they use apocalyptic for this.
Yes.
Which literally means unveiling or taking away the veil, right?
Right.
So the idea is it's there.
You just can't see it until the veil is removed.
So again, this is vision language again.
And this establishes that.
the way he would have come to know the God of Israel is through seeing the word of Yahweh.
Right?
Yeah.
And so that first verse means that Yahweh is rare. There's not many visions.
That means the knowledge of God is kind of lost to Israel.
And Samuel is being called as a prophet to counter that.
That also means that, right, when we talk about in the new
Testament. Saint John's Gospel, again being a very important center of this idea,
talking about people not being able to come to know God apart from Christ.
This is part and parcel of the same theology in the Old Testament.
There is this figure, there is this person, the word of Yahweh, through whom.
That's the only way. People come to know Yahweh through an encounter with
the word or with someone who the word sends out
Yeah, someone who does see the word and who even sends out to
Proclaim what he says. Yeah, which profits. Yeah, exactly profits end, you know later. Impossible. Yeah possible. Yeah, right
And so with within this story
Samuel's a kid he's sleeping and
He hears this voice calling out to him
And three times the voice calls out to it says, Hey, Samuel, Samuel, wake up, right?
And he thinks it's Eli because Eli's now an old man. He's the high priest.
Samuel's there helping him, right? So he goes running over to Eli to see what he wants.
And the the first couple of times Eli's like, go to bed. I didn't say anything, right?
Buzz off. Buzz up, young. If you're Dutch.
Right.
Since the back to the third time, you live figures out something.
going on. Right? I'm not calling you but clearly you're you're hearing someone call to you.
Yeah and what's interesting to me about that is that it's it sounds so much like a voice like a
human voice apparently that Samuel can think that it's Eli. Right. So it is it like thundering off
the rafters. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It is it like metallic sounding or yeah. Yeah. And so that
that third time he says okay
Well, next time, say, well, here I am.
See what it says to you.
Yeah. Speak, Lord, for your servant years.
Yeah.
And so he says, okay.
Right. And so then in verse 10 of that chapter,
we get the fourth time.
But we're told that Yahweh comes and stands
as at the other times, calling to him.
to him. He stands by his bed.
So that tells us that since it's as the other times all four times, again, it's not just
a voice calling out to him, but Yahweh has come in stood next to his bed.
There's a broadley.
A bodily presence.
Right.
And so after the call, he then, you know, Samuel responds to that time, he interacts
Right with...
with Yahweh the God of Israel, judgment is pronounced against Eli and his family.
And then in verses 20 and 21, it summarizes what just happened.
Yeah, okay, so it says this, and all Israel from Dan to Birshiba knew that Samuel was established
as a prophet of the Lord, and the Lord appeared again at Shiloh for the Lord revealed himself to
Samuel etchilo by the word of the Lord. And again, that's that review
is that sense of uncovering or unveiling or being displayed. Right. It's that same word. Yeah.
The Lord uncovered himself to Samuel by the word of the Lord. So the first time that verb is used,
it's used that the word of Yahweh had not been unveiled to him. And here it's said that he is
certainly a prophet because Yahweh revealed himself to him.
Yeah, by the word of the Lord. Yeah, right. Yeah. So he came to know the God of Israel through seeing
the Debaria way, the word of the word of the Lord.
So another similar example comes in the first chapter of Jeremiah. And this is actually Jeremiah's call to be a prophet. Yeah, which as I recall hearing you say,
say, you know, Saint Paul just totally cribs this describing his own
call, which I mean, rightfully, right? He's not he's not making
stuff up. But okay, so right, and that shows you how Saint Paul sees
Yeah, it's called to be an apostle. Yeah, that he sees it as
incognuity with the proof what the prophets were doing. Yeah, so
so Jeremiah one, four and five. This is Jeremiah speaking. Now
the word of the Lord came to me saying.
Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you and before you were born, I consecrated you.
I appointed you a prophet to the nations.
Right.
So the word of Yahweh comes to him, right?
It doesn't say he heard the word of Yahweh, right?
So unless you think like a sheath of loose leaf paper with these words on it floated
down out of the sky, right?
And led to Jeremiah's lap, which is very quickly not what it's saying, right?
Yeah.
This is the word of the Lord is someone who speaks, right?
And even though it's identified as the word of Yahweh,
he says, in the first person,
I formed you in the womb.
Yeah, I do you.
Yeah, so this is the word of Yahweh saying things
that only Yahweh could say, you know,
that He created Jeremiah, that He knew Him and consecrated Him,
and appointed Him to be a prophet to the nations.
Right, and then in
And verse 6, the very next verse, when Jeremiah responds, he calls him again, the Lord
Yahweh.
And you get the weird Lord, all caps God thing because again, Lord, Lord sounds weird.
Right.
In English.
And then in verse 9, we're told that Yahweh puts out his hand and touches Jeremiah's
mouth.
Hmm.
Yeah.
So if you had any doubts.
Yeah, another very bodily experience.
Right, that he was there in person. Right. He puts out his hand and touches his mouth. Yeah.
And he says in that after touching his mouth, behold, I've put my words plural in your mouth. Right. So the word capital W puts words, puts his words in the mouth of the prophet.
We mentioned all of these instances. Again, there's hundreds and hundreds of
the uses of these phrases, right?
the Bible, we can't go over all of them. But we mention all of them to give you a kind
of key for understanding when you read the Bible, when you see all these hundreds of instances
yourself, to understand what this phrase means, the word of the Lord or the word of God,
the word of Yahweh, right? So there's three things that I think are really important to understand
here. Number one is that this is a person. This is a person talking to people and appearing
to people.
Number
Number two, that again, that this person is seen and interacts bodily with people, with
the prophets especially.
And then the third one is that this person is Yahweh, is the God of Israel and is also
distinguished from Yahweh, meaning that this is God, this is a second person who is God.
There's God, the one most offensively called Yahweh, and then there's also Yahweh, the
word Yahweh that these are two
persons who are both Yahweh the God of Israel and yet they're not the same person, right?
They're distinguished from each other.
If you keep these three things in mind, whenever you see that phrase, the word of the Lord,
or the word of God in scriptures, you're going to be able to read that much more fruitfully,
I think, whenever you see that.
Again, hundreds of places that this is used.
Yeah, yeah, and so the rest of
This half we're going to talk about some sort of general examples and ways that plays out in different other parts of the Old Testament.
Yeah. Again, we can't go into detail on every single instance, but how that kind of plays out. So, for example, in what's called the Hexatook, right, which is when you lump in Joshua with the Pentateuch, right, or the Torah, right.
And there are valid reasons to do that, right?
Like, for example,
Joshua, it's in the book of Joshua that like the conquest and everything that gets started at the end of numbers and in Deuteronomy like comes to completion, right?
So there's sort of an arc of the story, right leading from Exodus to the end of Joshua.
Um, and even at the end of Joshua, right, the conquest is seen as sort of completing in a certain sense the promises to Abraham regarding the land.
So you have this arc from Genesis through Joshua there right from Genesis
12 all the way to the end
of Joshua. So there are reasons to do that thematically, right, and literally. And there are themes
that sort of run through all six. And one of those is that there's this way in which the phrase,
the word of the Lord, the Dabariya was used, vis-a-vis the behavior of the people, right? The people
are said to be rebelling against the word of the Lord.
Or...
offending against the word of the Lord or ignoring the word of the Lord.
Yeah, which doesn't mean they just broke a thing he said to them.
It means they're rebelling against this person.
Right. That would be a weird way of speaking.
Yeah. Right. I would if you're if you told your kid to do something and he didn't do it,
you wouldn't go to them and say, you have rebelled against the word which I spoke to you.
right I mean I may see that kind of thing
them but you might. That's fair. Okay. Most folks. My children, my children do complain
to me like why are you talking that way? Because it's awesome. Your house is just an issue
of Thor all the time by family. So, yeah. So, so you wouldn't say, you know, you rebelled
against the piece of paper on the fridge that listed your chores.
You say you were built against me, which we do have two or three of those.
You know, because it's an act of offense against the person who wrote the chores
or who gave the command, right?
That's who it's directed at.
Now, if we understand this identification of this figure,
we talked last time about the angel of the Lord who's there with them in person
during this stretch, right from from the exit
through Joshua, right, that they're actively rebelling against him. And then what did he say
in judges when he left, right? They had ignored him rebelled against him, grieved him,
right? All of those things. So there is this person whom they are rebelling against.
You know, we see there's a few interesting things we can touch on real quick, right? In the
songs
So like Psalm 18 verse 30.
Yeah, so this is interesting.
It says, this God, his way is perfect.
The word of the Lord proves true.
He is a shield for all those who take refuge in him.
So I mean, if, again, if you read this as the word of the Lord is just a thing that God says,
then it doesn't make sense that he would say immediately after that,
he is a shield for all those who take refuge in him.
word of the Lord is
this he who is this shield, you know, right? That is how he proves true. Is that he is a shield for all who take refuge in it. Right. Yep. Yep.
And then we even get some Holy Spirit as well in Psalm 33 or 32 in the Greek verses four through six. Okay. Yeah. So this is how this reads for the word of the Lord is upright.
and all his work is done in faithfulness. He loves righteousness and justice. The
this full of the steadfast love of the Lord, by the word of the Lord, the heavens were made,
and by the breath of his mouth, all their host. And for those who even know a little bit of
Hebrew, a Greek, you can guess that breath there is Rhoach in Hebrew and Pnevmati and Greek
spirit, right? It's the spirit is what's mentioned there, by the spirit of his mouth, all their host
remain. Right. And.
And so in verse 6 you get what is a reasonably common analogy in the Church fathers regarding
the Holy Trinity of God, His Word and the Breath that carries the Word that's coming right
out of this psalm.
But also notice that the Word of the Lord is associated with the making of the heavens,
so the setting in order and the spirit is then associated with the
with filling it with life, right? Those two aspects of creation that we talked about a few times on this show.
Yeah, and what you see all the way back in Genesis chapter 1.
Yeah. Yeah.
So okay, so Psalm 105, 19, again, this is just very brief, but
until what he had said came to pass the word of the Lord tested him,
which again doesn't make sense if you're just talking about a word.
You know, like you're not tested by a word. He's being tested by this person by the Lord himself
Right, and then of course very commonly and we saw specific examples of the word actually appearing to prophets usually if they're calling
but
there are also
That's also just a common phrase all through all of the prophets is the word of the Lord came to yeah
Yeah, this profit.
Yeah, right. And then when the prophet goes to pass on, right, that information encounters this
person, the word of the Lord is sent out to proclaim this. They will say, here the word of Yahweh,
here the word of the Lord, right? And then follow that up with the word of the Lord says,
The word of Yahweh says, yes.
the word says it's not and and the word reads this way, you know, or whatever, it's it's again he's
passing on a message because he saw and spoke with the word of the Lord face to face.
Right. And when it says the word of Yahweh says it's not like he then quotes the Torah.
Right. Right. This is new probably this is with the word of Yahweh came to me. He said,
right now I'm reeling that to you and it's
used interchangeably, right? In the same prophet, during the same oracle, it will alternate between
the word of Yahweh says and just Yahweh says. Yeah. Yeah. And it's interesting. I mean, one of the
pasts as we looked at, I suggest everybody looked this one up in Malachi chapter 1, which starts out
this way, right? The word of the Lord comes to him. And over and over again, then you get the Lord
of hosts says, the Lord of hosts says. So it's in that chapter in particular, it's underlined this idea
that the word of the
Lord is the Lord of hosts. He's the one who presides over the armies of God.
Then there's this pattern that you especially see in other places too but especially in first and
second kings. One locus where this happens a whole bunch of times is specifically in first kings
or third kingdoms, 13. There's seven times just in that one chapter where it talks about something
being done.
by the word of Yahweh, not in the sense of like somehow that strengthened me, but in the sense of the word of Yahweh did this thing.
Yeah, right. There's a person he's doing stuff.
The word of Yahweh said the word of Yahweh did, right, where it's an agent, which means it's a person.
Right. Yeah.
And there's another one and this is a passage that's to be familiar to all of us who listen to this.
So by now, first Kings 22, this is where A-hab is about to get it.
And the prophet, Mikeia, comes to him and actually tells him, warns him, warns him what's about to happen.
And he still doesn't repent.
But so Mikeia says to him in verse 19, therefore here, the word of the Lord,
I saw the Lord sitting on his throne and all the host of heaven standing beside him on his right hand and on his left.
again that's
a reference to the word of the Lord as the Lord of hosts, the one who's presiding in the divine
council. Right. And he's the one particularly presiding in the council and sort of issuing the
decree. Yeah, right. He's the spokesman. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, I mean, all of these are using
these very sort of personal terms to talk about the word of the Lord. He does things. He says things,
you know, he's the spokesman. He's the ruler of the divine council.
Again, this is not...
not just the words that God says.
This is something much, much bigger than that.
Right.
And so what we're going to see when we come back in the third half, and we finally now
get to our actual topic.
No, we finally get to the first chapter of Saint John's Gospel.
We're going to see Saint John is going to take all of this from the Hebrew scriptures,
on what would become the Christian Old.
Testament. You take all of these ideas and this is going to be the basis for what he has to tell us
concerning Christ in his gospel and he's going to lay that out in the prologue here at the beginning.
All right, well, we're going to take a short break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen
Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-236-
7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Big in Heaven, a collection of short stories
available now on the Ancient Faith Book Store.
Sometimes poignant, sometimes funny, sometimes heartbreaking,
sometimes convicting.
These stories of life in an inner city,
immigrant orthodox parish are guaranteed
to shake your assumptions
and make you see your life and faith in...
a new way. They are not for the faint of heart, but they are very much for all who want
to embrace the truth more fully.
I needed to ask Rusk over for help, cleaning, polishing, carrying, in or out, any work in
the church the woman was astalled, a tallodish, you could count on, no one knew her suffering,
never bothered to look into our eyes. It surprised me the most of the church
that's ain't Alexander the whirling-durish parish.
Didn't even know her name.
It wasn't anything they'd thought about.
To find this book and others like it,
you can go to store.enginefei.com.
Again, that is store.enginefei.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
All right, well, welcome back.
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Once again, this is not a live show.
So don't, don't call tonight.
We'll get back to your calls next time.
But we do have a voicemail that was left for us by Fortuni, who asked this.
Father's Bless.
This is Potany from Uncle Moreport.
I know you've spoken about this a little bit before, but in the beginning of John, when he talks about the logos, I've heard even Orthodox people explain this as being entirely related to Scripture that Scripture is kind of the only thing that's meant here that Scripture is the primary reference.
And from what you've said about the word of the word kind of
to people, particularly in the Old Testament, it feels like that's not a great understanding.
But I would like some more clarity on this, I'm sure other people would. Can you talk a little
bit about what Logos means and what the word of the Lord means in the Gospel of John?
Thank you so much for all you do. Okay, so I mean on some level we've already kind of debunked
this idea that the word of the Lord is a reference to the Bible.
I think probably the best way to really put the nail in this coffin.
As you said, we're going to look at the beginning of St. John's Gospel, right?
Right. Right.
And she specifically got referred even to the even here, which is kind of one of the
weirder places to try to.
Yeah.
Ramrod that definition.
I do wonder if she was dressed as a bat while phoning in.
She has threatened to come to age
faith events dressed as a bat. So this is, I mean, it is possible that she is preparing herself
for that eventuality. But try as she might, she will never know what it's like to really be well.
She should just be a person to be the one to break it to. Yes. Sorry for any. You may know what,
you may know what it's like to be back girl or bat woman, but not what it's like to be an actual
bat. It's okay. It's okay. Well, the food is better for us humans. So just put in that. Yes.
Because I mean, although maybe it's...
great for them. Maybe they love it. But yeah, we'll never
announce possible because we don't know what it's like to be
about. Yeah. So all right. So Jay St John's St John's, this is
called the prologue, the first 18 verses of St John's first
chapter in his gospel. And notably, this is read in the in the
Orthodox Church. Now, I know it's a generalization, but I mean
99.99% of Orthodox churches.
Read this Gospel.
at at Pasca at the Fisa Lurzer resurrection and that's the only time it doesn't get read for
anything else. And if you don't, you're the one who asked to explain it, not me.
Yes, right. You have the burden of proof. Yeah, although I mean, it should be I should point out
that in the the the small percentage of Orthodox churches, namely the the Western right churches
that that don't read this for for Pasca, they actually read it at the end of every mass,
like this is what they call the last gospel so they're reading it all the time
That's overdoing it.
It's not special anymore if you do it every week.
That's what they taught me back before I was Orthodox.
Anyway, yeah, there are special things I do every day.
And there's special every time.
Yes, at most three times a year,
whether you need it or not.
That's all I'm saying.
So anyway, it's really underlined in one way or another in Christian liturgical tradition.
and
So let's just dive in in the beginning was the word.
Yeah, you could continue. Oh, you'll make you go on.
I will continue. I'll read the first couple of verses. Okay.
So this is this is the ESV and we're going to kind of take apart a lot of the translation here as we go.
In the beginning was the word and the word was with God and the word was God.
He was in the beginning with God.
So
Yeah, so the first verse then, I mean, and we're gonna point this out. I'm gonna read a little bit of Greek
Uh, the first verse goes like this and are he in Oligos K Oligos in Proston Theon K Theos in Oligos. That's how it goes in Greek
Yes, so how how how let's let's pull this apart bit by bit because I mean this is
This is really important. Yeah, and and when we say we're pulling apart the translation right
This is not an attack upon the ESB or any other English translation.
No, it's not that much different.
Yeah, yeah.
No, it's like translating John along.
It's sort of like, let's take this apart to see how it works kind of thing.
Right, right.
Because, and you know, the ESB, like most English translations, was done by a committee, right?
Yes.
They may question what that means because I still hold that no committee has ever done
anything, right?
person on a committee did it.
Right.
To the other ones.
you know, argued about it.
I argued about what that one person did.
Editing half-but.
But the point being when something goes through a committee like that,
especially with, since the ESV is the RSV,
we're talking about a committee that had various types of Protestant folks working on it,
Roman Catholic folks involved,
even Orthodox folks involved,
You're gonna have to be really non-committal
biologically
Right. If you're talking about any passage with important theology, you're going to have to do a lot of punts, lots of, lots of ends. Right.
Because again, a translation is an interpretation. Like there's just no way around that. You know.
Right. And so we're just, we're just going to dig a little deeper past the committee. Yeah.
Yeah. To get closer to the text itself.
Yeah. So, so NRHe, that's how it starts out, right?
So what is right what does that mean?
It starts
within the beginning. Right. And that should take us back to the book of Genesis, which
begins the exact same way. Right. And it'd be Greek with those exact words. So we're going
back to that point of Genesis 11. And what we're told by the second half of that first clause,
Now in English they're following the order of the words in the
when they say in the beginning was the word.
Yeah, it's exactly word for word literally in that case.
Yeah, so the word there that's translated was, which is
in it, new, new, new, new.
I will let you take all the heat from the Greeks.
Okay, okay, I'm throwing you under the bus.
I'll take it.
So I don't say it in that arasemy in way.
So try not to anyway.
Yeah, the question is, are you correctly saying it in the
Anyway, I don't know.
I'm doing my best.
Yeah.
So with Greek, the tense system, we tend to think of verb tense purely in terms of time
in English because that's most of what it does in English.
Past, present, future.
Yeah.
Right.
it's telling us primarily when the activity was taking place.
That's described by the verb.
That's not the case in ancient Greek.
In ancient Greek, there is a temporal element.
It's not that there's nothing to do with time.
But the primary thing that tense tells you in ancient Greek
is it's telling you the type or the quality of the activity.
So for example, there are two
different Greek tenses that get translated by the English pass tense. So this is
was, was is pass tense, right? There's is was will be, right? Present pass
feature in English. But that pass that was does two different tenses. So one of
Most of those tenses is what's called the airst tense, which is spelled A O
R-I-S-T. And people say crazy things about the airst, but in actuality, it
ancient Greek, the airst tense is basically telling you pretty much nothing about
the activity. It's sort of the neutral, the neutral tense. It's just telling you
that something happened. Yeah, neutral past tense is it where it's pretty close to
English past tense. Right. Well, it ends up it's it's not again the temporal
element is not the primary element but
But if something has happened that means whoever's talking or writing about it, it's going to be in their past because it's happened already, right?
So the facto is going to end up being in the past.
The other tense that gets translated as past has a stronger temporal element.
You are very deliberately saying that this is something that was going on in the past.
And that is what's called the Greek imper-
tense. Yeah, which usually in English an imperfect verb is one that you know is typically
a gerund you know ends with I.N.G. right so like was being or had been being and you know
like yeah or I mean I am walking that's an imperfect that's a present imperfect right I'm
talking you know anyway right right where is uh
This is, it has that sort of continuous activity, right?
This is something that was going on for a while,
but that while is in the past, right?
So a sort of very literal way of translating
that first clause would be,
in the beginning, the word was being.
Mm.
Yeah, or meaning had been being.
Right, yeah.
or already was.
Hmm right so in the beginning when we go back there to Genesis 1 1
When God starts creating everything
The word the logos already was already was existing already was being
Right, yeah, yeah, which again doesn't make any sense if you're trying to say that this is about the Bible
Right
Or even just words plural. Yeah
Yeah, yeah God was already taught
That doesn't make sense, right?
But this also then is the, is pre-existence, right?
Not just pre-existence of when Jesus was born on earth, right?
But pre-existence is in pre-existing the creation.
Yeah, right.
In the beginning when everything was about to be created,
the word had been being already.
Already it was.
Yeah.
Right.
And then...
And so then the second clause is, right, after the hand.
So yeah, here we go.
Right in.
Let me know how terrible my pronunciation is.
Que los los impostos de un.
Right.
So that's what's usually translated.
And the word was with God.
Right.
That in there is again, the same had been being or was already
was or was being.
was.
being, right? Yeah. And then we've got the preposition pros, right? So prepositions
in Greek do different things, depending on what type of verb and what type of object
they're put with. Right? So pros can mean motion towards, right? So if this was a verb
of movement. Right. So if you said I was walking...
the store, right?
I was walking to the store.
Toward the store, right?
And then it would depend on the verb tense.
I said walking, it would be toured.
It was past tense.
I walked, it would be I walked to the store, right?
Because it's at the past.
Right.
So, but this is a being verb, right?
Not a verb of motion.
And so, pros in this case,
with is not a bad translation,
but it really even has more of the concept of act.
really even has more of the concept of
at like co-location. Like there is a house at this street corner. Right. Right. So you're
saying there's the street corner is there and the house that they're both there. Yeah.
And so the word was co-located was at God. Although it's not just God here. It's not just
they on. It's toned. They on. So what's why is that important that there's this definite
article there
well there's an article and
Excuse me. Don't be so definite. Yeah.
Yeah.
Greek in this area did not technically have a definite article.
Yeah. Yeah.
Sort of demonstrative. Mostly, right?
Yeah.
So, this article is here because this is a common way in Greek when you read Jewish texts
that are in Greek.
There are certain distinctions that are made in...
certain ways in the Hebrew, right? So for example, in the Hebrew of the Hebrew scriptures,
it's very rare, not completely absent, but it's very rare that you see the way that God
of Israel referred to as just ale. Yeah, the word forgot. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, right. Yeah,
which you spell like L in English.
You almost always see it in the plural.
right? We've talked before about what's going on with the pure plural a little bit, but
that's also a way of distinguishing between because ale was also the name of a particular god,
the father of bail. Yeah, a canonite pagan god, right? Right, and so a way of distinguishing, right?
between Yahweh, the God of Israel, and Al was to not use that exact form of the word.
Right? And so God without an article can be used in a lot of ways in Greek, right? It can be indefinite. It can mean a God, right?
It can even be sometimes used to just sort of mean divine, right? Or divinity as a concept, right?
And so one of the ways...
that that would be expressed the idea that this is God the most high God right is by putting the article there in Greek the God right.
And so we of course don't translate it as the God because that would be weird right yeah.
But so this is saying that the word is there this again is is co-located with God the God right.
right look creator god yo they got a visual
meaning they're both existing together.
They're co-located here at the beginning
before anything is created.
There's a distinction. There's two persons
that are both there at the beginning.
Right. Yeah. Okay, so the last clause is
Que Theos in Ologos.
Yes. Yeah. Now notice. Yeah, go ahead.
As I say, which literally is, and God was being...
the word. Right. Yeah. And but in that word order, it's
important to note there's no deaf or there's no, you have me
doing it now. There's no article there. Sorry. It's just
K the oh right. Yeah. So it's not saying that the God was the
word. Right. It's not contradicting what we just saw and
saying there is no distinction. Right? Right.
There's no, there is an article before logos.
There's not an article before the os, which means that it's being predicated.
Yes.
So the word is predicate, which is why usually in English they flip the order and say the
word was God.
Right.
Rather than with that same kind of t-shirt was being.
Yes.
Exactly.
That in, in, in, it's three times in that verse was already being.
Right.
That rules out all of your what we now call adoptionist crystalline.
Jesus. Yep. Right. That Christ at some point became God. Yeah. Right. This is saying he was already being God before anything was created. Right. That this is not a sort of later thing.
And and these need to be ruled out. You say, well, why would that need to be ruled out? Wasn't that like a second century hair seer or something?
We've been talking about this second figure,
this second power in heaven, the second...
figure in the Old Testament, there were lots of going theories within Second Temple Judaism as to who
this was. Yeah, so this is John saying, no, no, no, no, no, this is what's true. Right. So this
is this is pre-human, right? So this means it can't be here are some of the theories. It can't be
enoc, it can't be Adam, it can't be Moses, it can't be David, right? Because this one is in the beginning.
right before any of that right so you have
already here, just in that first verse, right? Just like was done with the
Dabariya weha in the Old Testament, you have this figure who's distinguished from
Yahweh the God of Israel and identified with Yahweh the God of Israel.
Right. Yeah. And made co-aturnal with Yahweh the God of Israel. Yeah. Yeah. Okay.
And then you get verse two, which reads this way, utos in anarchy prostontheon.
you
which is sort of doubling down, it's what we call an opposition for the first verse.
It's just restating it in a slightly different way. Uto's right is, that's the demonstrative.
This one. Yeah, this one. This one. He's underlined. This one had been being, or was it already being
in the beginning, co-located with the God.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, again, that's really clumsy to say it that way, which is why you would probably
never put that in a Bible translation into English.
But that's why it's useful for us to kind of like, is it take it apart a little bit and
then have a look inside.
You know, so you can see what's going on there as best as we possibly can.
Right.
And so now we've started at Genesis 1-1, right, with where...
Where is the word?
Where is the Jabariya way?
Where is this person, the word of the Lord?
At the beginning, he's right there, right?
Colocated with God.
He is both identified with the God of Israel, the Creator God, and he is distinguished from
the person of the Creator God.
And so now we move forward into Genesis 2, one verse 2.
John 1.
Yeah, John 1, first year, yeah.
Which is moving into, no.
We're going in there.
I know.
John 1 verse 3.
We're moving it to Genesis 2.
Okay.
Yeah.
I mean, in a lot of ways, that's what St. John is doing.
He's recapitulating Genesis.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this reads in English, all things were made through him.
And without him was not anything made, that was made.
And I'll just read that real quick and Greek.
that
the after a yenato,
ke choris,
after a yenato,
ude,
en o,
ye,
ye-yonen.
Yeah, sorry.
I don't know how the panda got in there,
but Honda.
No.
Yes.
Pandemonium.
So,
right.
And so this is remembered.
This is over too, right?
In the beginning, what has got to do?
He creates the heavens of the earth, right?
Right.
And the earth is without forward void, right?
So we have that statement first.
So, um,
when it's literally saying all things through him came into being.
Yeah, it's not made exactly.
It's not, you know, Pio or Czizzo, right, which is a user words from making something.
It's or creating.
Yeah, creating.
Yeah, it's a Yenato came into came into being, you know, yeah.
Yeah, came came to be.
Yeah.
So all things
came to me through him and then to clarify that the second clause and separate from him apart from him.
Okay, what is up to cut off from him almost literally.
Yeah.
Not one thing that came into being came into being.
Right.
So you have this category.
All the things that came into being.
All the things.
Right.
Oh
All the things, right?
Everything that's a thing, right?
All these came into being, came into being through him.
Nothing in that category came into being apart from him, right?
What does that imply?
Well, that implies he is not in that category.
Mm.
Yeah, he's not a creative day.
Right.
He is not in the category of things that came into being.
Sorry, not sorry, Aryans.
Yeah, right.
sort of.
definitionally there. And then secondly, that he is this instrument, right? The
logo says the instrument through which God creates, right? And what is creation, as
we've said several times, it's putting things in order, right? Meaning the
logo says here for St. John, both this creative intermediary, right? So he's
already serving this function as an intermediary between God and the creation.
And he's also then the organizing principle, right?
The logos in that sense of structure, right?
Of rational structure within the created order, right?
He is then that principle by which things are put in order.
Yeah, you can just imagine a file of Alexandria going, okay?
Mm-hmm, yeah, uh-huh, okay.
So yeah, he's really getting bored with all of this so far.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
Yeah, okay. So now, I mean, it's been really interesting up to this point, but now this is going to,
this is the part that a lot of this was a little bit new to me and just is awesome. So I just have to
say that to everybody. So versus four and five, I mean, I don't mean it's new to me in the sense I've
never read this before, but understanding what's going on here in a deeper way. That's what's you have,
you have been to a Pascus. I have been. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Many, many, many times now.
Okay, so verses four and five in here.
was life and the life was the light of men. The light shines in the darkness and the darkness
has not overcome it. Which, okay, so the way I had been understanding this verse was essentially
talking about Jesus as the light of the world. Which, I mean, he says that, right? In another place,
I am the light of the world. You know, and he's shining in the darkness and dark, you know, so forth.
But, but okay, the life was the
light of men, that's something that's kind of interesting. Right? Yeah. So let's go. Yeah,
of course, what's going on inside this? So we, we, we're still in Genesis 1. Yes. Yeah. Right.
We're now at the first day of creation. Let there be light. Right. And the light and the darkness
are separated. And so this is identifying
the light of that first day of creation, right?
What is that light?
Right?
Because the sun moon and stars haven't been created yet.
Right.
That's day four, which is in parallel to this,
but isn't this.
Right.
And this is identifying that light that shown in the darkness,
and the darkness is not a comment that was separated, right?
That pushed back the darkness, right?
On that first day, that light is the life that is in Christ.
the life that is in the logos.
Right. So which is the life of God?
Yeah. So just make sure every
following along here when God says
let there be light.
This is the, John, St. John is
interpreting that here is saying that
that light is the life of Christ
shining out from Him.
That's what's going on here.
And it's about to get even cooler.
Right, it's the
Life, right, it's the life of God that that that is in Christ that that shines for that this is later on in St. John's Gospel, right?
Father has given it to the Son to have life in himself, right? Right. Um,
so, but notice also, right, that that life was the light of it's translate of man, but it's actually humanity.
Right. This is from from Anthropos, right? And the other word for man is going to be used later in the same passage.
So...
It's a deliberate thing.
Yeah, yeah.
So this is humanity.
Right.
I mean, the way that I've, you know, generally have understood
that is it's like, oh, yes, he enlightens, you know, mankind.
You know, they're receiving light from him, which I mean,
it's not wrong, right?
It's not wrong, but it's actually way deeper than that.
Right.
Because there aren't any humans yet.
If we remember the first day of creation.
We have to remember that this is still
the first day of creation.
Right.
So what does that mean?
This is telling us that this relationship between the life of God that is in Christ, that
is in the logos, that is in the eternal logos.
This life of Christ has this purpose of being the light of men.
So that means that humanity is in view.
sharing his life with humanity.
through Christ, through his word, is in view as the purpose for the beginning of creation.
From that moment of let there be light, that humanity is already the purpose.
Right, in view. Right. And not just the creation of humans to roam around on this world.
Right, right, but forgot to shit
his divine life with humans.
Yeah. And in case you kind of wonder like are they going out on a limb here saying that
that's what St. John is saying that this is about the first day of creation, right? In case
you wonder that St. Paul does the exact same thing in 2 Corinthians 4 6 where he says,
for God who said, let light shine out of darkness has shown in our hearts to give the light
of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus.
Jesus Christ.
St. Paul saying exactly the same thing here.
He's expanding a little bit on it, you know, talking about the glory of God, the face of
Jesus Christ.
But it's again that same thing, that the light that shines in the darkness at the very
beginning of creation is sent out to shine into the hearts of human beings to give them
the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ.
That's exactly what St. Paul says.
That comes to us through Christ.
And so this means that what we call...
theosis, right? Sharing in God's life, becoming like God, becoming sons of God. This is the purpose of creation.
Right. And it begins at the moment of creation. Right. Yeah. And so the light that we're talking about is the life of God in Christ,
it's theosis, it's salvation. That's what the light is. The light is not just another way as we're going to see here in a minute.
It's not just another way to refer to Christ poetically.
It's like they were talking about salvation.
And this is all through the Old Testament,
the main language that's used to talk about theosis,
to talk about salvation is shining like the stars,
from Abraham to Daniel, right?
Right?
To the book of wisdom, right?
That the righteous shine like the stars
in the day of the Lord.
And the stars, we know of that association
with angels, with the angelic sons of God.
So
This is the light that's being talked about.
Yeah, that's so cool.
So yeah, the light is the life of God in Christ.
It is salvation shines out in the darkness.
I mean, it becomes salvation the sense
that when human beings cooperate with that, right?
Then it becomes, but it's Christ doing his,
his, he's begins to save us from the very beginning
of the moment of the beginning of creation.
That's just astonishing.
That's really cool.
Okay, so moving on.
Yeah, yeah.
But say John is not done.
Yeah, he's not done.
I know.
I could just say goodnight right now.
I really could.
So okay, verse six.
I'm going to read six to nine.
There was a man sent from God whose name was John.
He came as a witness to bear witness about the light
that all might believe through him.
him. He was not the light but came to bear with him.
witness about the light, the true light, which gives light to everyone, was coming into
the world. Right? So, I mean, just to disambiguate a touch here when St. John the Evangelist,
the Apostle, says there was a man sent from God, his name was John. He's not talking about
himself. It's on, it's John the forerunner, John the Baptist, who's being mentioned here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right. And so St. John, right, is this
man, right? Now, I notice he's a man right off the bat. He's human who's sent from God.
And he's sent to witness, to bear witness. What that means is that's not about testifying,
right? Like if you're called to give testimony in some kind of court case or adjudication,
right? To testify about the light. Now, or goes translation, they have that all might believe
through him.
It's not clear, believe what?
Right?
Yeah, no, it's become faithful.
Yeah.
Right?
We go faithful.
Because what is it that he's bearing witness about?
The light.
Right?
Remember, the light is this salvation.
St. John comes to prepare the way.
Right?
To prepare the path.
So he testifies to the path.
right, to salvation, right? He was not the light. He didn't have salvation in himself, right?
St. John didn't come to save everyone himself, but he came to bear witness to it, right? And then
we finally read that the true light which enlightens its every human or all humans, right, was coming
into the world. Now that that was the pronoun that's used there is a neuter pronoun,
Right, the low...
is referred to throughout this passage with masculine singular pronouns.
Yeah, right. So, yeah. So, the true light again is not the person of the
logos. It's not the person of Christ. The true light here is that salvation, that
life which is in Christ, the life of God which is in Christ, which is now
coming into the world. Right. So, salvation. Yeah, exactly. So, again, you know,
Christ does.
does it another point say I am the light of the world, but this is not what this use of light is about.
It's, you know, in this case, light is the thing that's coming from Christ, rather than being used to identify him.
And as you said, there's differences and pronouns here which kind of let you know that that's what's going on.
Right. Right.
So, we now, when we get into the next section,
Right. People are going to be tempted to jump ahead. Right. Because you say, oh, well, we're
done with Genesis now. Now we've jumped all the way to St. John the Forerunner. Right. But
something interesting is going to happen here because of the next few verses that we're about to
read. St. John, the evangelist is still in the Old Testament. Yeah. He's describing the Old
testament period of the prophets. So why did he talk about St. John first? Because St.
John the Forerunner is the paradigm for the prophets even though he's the last one.
Right. Yeah. This is another thing that was a little surprising to me, but it makes way more
sense to read it this way that St. John is here again recapitulating the whole of the Old Testament
within just a few verses here, right? Right. And so St. John sort of supremely
testifies to the way of salvation, right?
Here's the capstone of the prophets.
He's the...
seal of the prophets, right? But all of the prophets of the period of the prophets of the Old Testament
were doing that. Right. Right. Exactly. Yeah. So, okay. So moving on, I'm going to read verses 10 through
13. He was in the world and the world was made through him yet the world did not know him.
He came to his own and his own people did not receive him. But to all who did receive him,
who believed in his name.
He gave the right to become children of God, who were born not of blood nor of the will
of the flesh nor of the will of men but of God.
So yeah, so let's take this apart because this actually is a big sweep of history.
It's not simply talking about when Craig, you know, St. John is actually not talking about
what's about to happen in the rest of his gospel.
This is still prologue, right?
This is still not what, you know, yeah.
Alright, it's-
spoilers, the incarnation is going to happen in verse 14.
Yeah, right. So when it says he was in the world and the world was made through him yet the world
did not know him. That's talking about that's before the incarnation still. Right.
That's before the word becomes flesh. The word was in was being. This is that same tense was being in
the world continuously. Right. Before he became flesh and the world was made through him as we saw,
be created the whole world.
But the world out there did not know him, the nations, right, did not know him.
Right. Right. And so then it moves forward. He moves forward and says,
he came to his own and his own people did not receive him. Right. And this is now Moses.
Right. Right. He came to his own. He came to his own people. Right. He was in the world.
But then he came particularly, the logos, the word of God came particularly to his own
people.
people and his own people did not receive him. Right. He appears over and over again to
the prophets and they bring him to them, but he over and over again, they, excuse me,
they over and over again reject him and turn away from him and rebel against him. That's
what this verse 11 is. It's, it's, it's, it's not about the rejection that he's about
to experience as the incarnate Christ. This is about the unfaithfulness of Israel and the
old covenant.
Right.
Though that is certainly part-
of this pattern. Oh yeah, sure, sure, sure, the story of the old testament is the story
of God drawing close to his people Israel and Israel rejecting him. Yeah, right over and
over again. And that's verse 12, right? Um, or verse 11 verse verse 12 then, right? But
but to whoever received him is what it sort of literally says, right, whoever received
So again, there's this remnant idea.
So there was this group with...
Israel who did receive him even though Israel as a whole his people as a whole did not.
And to those he gave, he gave them authority. It's exucy and Greek. It's like freedom to act.
Right. It's like agency, right. He gave them the agency to become children of God.
Yeah, and this is children here by the way, it's not sons.
It's techno which I mean which you know obviously includes sons, but it's it's
general in general right yeah, but it is the same kind of idea right it's this is talking about
theosis again right so it's not just that there were prophets pointing that way it's that the
those who did receive him and did follow that way right that so again Christ is the means the logos
the word of God. Christ, he's the means of salvation in the Old Testament.
also. Right. Yeah. Right. Sorry, dispensationalist friend. Sorry, not so. So, right. And notice also
this language, right. They translate who believed in his name. I don't know exactly what that would
mean. But it's more those who were faithful to his name. Right. Remember what we talked about
last time with the angel of the Lord. Right? This one who had his name placed in him.
Right, Tabernacle of the Temple are the places where Yahweh put his name.
Right, those who were faithful to his name, they received him and who were faithful to his name.
They're the ones who received this.
Yeah.
And then just in case you're not clear on exactly what this agency to become children of God is,
verse 13 makes it pretty clear that we're talking about theosis because they're born, right?
right?
gotten literally. Yeah, not of blood, meaning physical birth, right? Where there's blood, right?
Nor of the will of the flesh will keep it PG. You can guess what the will of the flesh is
referring to, right? In terms of producing children, uh, nor of the will of eight. Then this man
is a man, it's a near, it's a word for a man, not for the will of a man. A guy decided he wanted
to have a child, right? Uh, but of God, they're begotten of God. Right. That's how they become
Yeah, and
And just, you know, again, to underline this,
St. Paul writes in Romans 8 verses 20 through 23,
essentially this same kind of thing.
He says, for the creation was subjected to futility,
not willingly, but because of him who subjected it,
in hope that the creation itself will be set free
from its bondage to corruption
and obtain the freedom of the glory of the children of God.
For we know that the whole creation has been
groaning together in the pains of childbirth until now,
Enough.
only the creation, but we ourselves, who have the first fruits of the Spirit, grown inwardly as we
wait eagerly for adoption as sons, the redemption of our bodies. So the St. Paul again saying that the whole
telos of creation, its whole purpose is the revelation of the sons of God, the adoption as sons
that were born of the will of God and that's the purpose of creation itself.
right there and that we're now in the stage of waiting eagerly for that because it hasn't yet come
to its fullness. Right. Right. That's now in verse 14. Now we get to what St. John's gospel is
going to be about. Yeah, this is about the incarnation. And this is yeah, and St. John's gospel,
remember, it doesn't have a birth narrative. Right. Right. It doesn't this, I mean, I'm really,
I mean that's kind of what's going on here.
Yeah. Okay. So verse 14 and the word became flesh and dwelt among us. And we have seen his glory.
Glory as of the only son from the father, full of grace and truth.
So I mean, the first thing there is, again, this is that language of the word. And he came to be
the same word same logo we were talking about from back in Genesis 1
Yeah, yeah, right at all through Israel's history right yeah and then
Dwell to among us which is okay, but it actually says
Tented or tabernacle right you get instructions. Yeah, tabernacle. There's a real literal yeah, yeah
Which which has this sense of you know, it's it's a sojourning its temporary
Right, um, it's not he didn't build a palace amongst us
He he tended among us. He tabernacle among us
Right?
And...
And also then Christ as, I mean, later on in St. John's Gospel, we're going to get,
you know, destroy this temple and I'll rebuild it in three days.
And St. John, hopefully, gives us the editorial comment.
By the way, he was referring to the temple of his body, right?
Right.
And so that's how we have to understand this glory language, right?
Because what happens in the tabernacle?
Yes.
The glory of God.
It's filled with the, the ephanic glory cloud, right?
The glory of God comes and fills the tabernacle.
And so.
The the logos that who becomes flash
Tabernacles among us and the glory of God the presence of God is is within him, right?
And this is glory now
Here we go. Big was she read
Yes, of the only son from the father. Yeah, and in some translations you get of the only begotten
Right from the father which it doesn't have the word son there
it's more at all yeah exact at all
I mean, that's a sort of a, again, every translation is an interpretation.
It's monoyenuous is how it is in its inflected form there.
Right. And so there's a couple of different verbs that are a couple of different words
that can end up giving you monoyenese essentially and then it gets declined.
And so only begotten is what you'll see in like the King James, right? And that kind of thing.
Right. So why would we say that it doesn't necessarily mean that here? Well, that's context, right?
So we just had in verse 13, right? The use of that verb begotten, that exact verb,
to talk about the ones who become the children of God. Right? So if now in the very next
verse, St. John says that Christ is the only one who has begotten. That doesn't make sense
that it contradicts itself. Right. Right. Right. The other meaning of monoyanese, right,
is of its own genus, meaning unique. Yeah. One of a kind. Literally one, a single of a
kind. Right, right. And so
Even if we're carrying over the begotten idea because we do have here for the first time in this passage
Othos here is referred to as the Father
Right, it's the same person right so if you want to carry that idea we still want to say that Christ is
Unique among sons, right?
Right, you can be we got right he's different than other children of God or sons of God right so the uniqueness is what's being
and emphasized.
Yeah, minimal. However you translate the word
You need to have some sense of Christ being unique
right and but but further in the context here, right?
It's the one who is uniquely from the Father
Yeah, right why would he need to say?
From the Father you in a unique sense well because he's he's just talked about remember when he brought up Saint John the
for a runner he was carefully distinguishing.
Yes.
There was a man sent from God.
Yeah.
Right.
And so, and St. John was the paradigm then for the other prophets.
So, there are these other men said from God.
Right.
Christ is uniquely from the Father.
Christ is from the Father in a different sense.
Right.
He goes for the Father in a different sense than prophets.
are also sent by God.
right? This is not, this is a different thing. This is unique. And backing up that interpretation
is the fact that in the very next verse verse 15, St. John the evangelist returns to St. John the
forerunner with his parenthetical comment to differentiate them again. Yeah, which again the
parentheses are not in the original Greek text, but it's a good, you know, it makes sense to interpret
with you know, translate with parentheses.
Okay, so verse 15, John bore witness about him and cried out, this was he of whom I said,
he who comes after me ranks before me because he was before me.
Right.
And that's literally with that verb tense again, he was being before me.
He existed before I existed.
Yeah.
Right.
So St. John is one of those people and things that comes into being.
Whereas Christ always was being.
Right.
This is important.
because in the way that traditional cultures tend to think, whatever comes after something
else usually is lesser or lower rank.
So every son is obedient to his father and his father is greater than he is the way
that it generally goes.
And so St. John is saying, look, even though he's coming after me, like I'm here on the
scene first and John is literally just a few months older, right?
He's saying even though he comes after me, he's actually before me.
ranks before me because you
always was being. He is from a bold, you know, and so I'm actually the lesser person here.
Right. Right. He's the he's the newcomer. Right. So again, this is not there is now in the incarnation.
This is a new thing. Right. There was this pattern he talked about in the Old Testament.
But now this is a break of pattern, right?
The word becoming flesh is not just another instant.
existence, right, of the word coming to humanity the way he came to humanity throughout the
Old Testament, right?
This is now different, right, in a different sense, right?
And then that's what's developed further in verses 16 and 17.
Yeah, okay.
So those read like this, for from his fullness, we have all received grace upon grace.
For the law was given through Moses, Grayson,
truth came through Jesus Christ.
And you notice I emphasized, and we'll talk about this second here, given through Moses,
grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.
But probably the first thing I think that to me, um, underlines what's going on in these
two verses is that phrase that gets translated by the ESV is grace upon grace.
But you said you think it should be, it, that it should be grace after grace.
Right.
Yeah.
Yes.
grace. Both of the things mentioned in verse 17 are in the category grace. Yeah. Right.
The Torah, the law, is in the category grace. Sorry Martin Luther. Sorry not. We've had a
several of those. Yeah. Right. So, uh, right. So it's grace after grace, right. And then
174 that's because yeah right right so in both cases
So verse 16, because, right.
And that's a, why is it different?
Right. How is it different?
It's, yeah.
It's given in this case.
That's the verb through Moses.
Well, the first, first.
How is, how is the incarnation of Christ,
the inflection of the word?
How is that different from that pattern?
Right. It's different because,
from the fullness of the logos,
We have all received grace after grace.
Yes.
Right. Okay. Because right. Yes. The first grace. Grace. Grace number one is that the law was given
through Moses, the verb being given. Right. Right. It's coming from someone else. Right. There is a
giver and it isn't Moses. Right. Right. Right. Right. It wasn't given by Moses. It was given through
it. So someone else gave it. Who? Right. The logos. Right. That was part of that Old Testament pattern.
right so I was given
was but grace and truth came and that came is that came into being word again.
Now, you know, in this kind of context, it has an idea like arrived.
Right. Right.
Oh, came into this world, right?
Arrived, right?
Through Jesus Christ.
Right. And I at least my understanding of part of why we shouldn't
translate that as come into being exactly is because grace and truth are not like
objects. They're not created objects.
Right.
There are things that didn't exist.
Right, right, right, exactly.
Right, they arrived.
Right, they arrived through the person of Jesus Christ, right?
And both of these are the logos as the agent, because the logos is Jesus Christ who is
full of grace and truth, right?
As we saw in verse 14.
And the logos is the one who gave the Torah through Moses.
Right. The logos is behind both of those. But now he has arrived. Yeah. So he is present. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Fully present. So saying that it might make people think the verse 18 doesn't make any sense.
Because the first thing it says, and this really is a wrap-up verse here, everybody. Yeah.
No one has ever seen God.
The only God who is at the father's side, he has made...
him known. Okay, so how can St. John say no one has ever seen God given everything that he just said?
Right. So this isn't a retcon, right? Where it's like all that stuff where the city saw God and
they'll never forget about it. Yeah. Right. Right. So he mentions the Father here. Right. Right.
No one has seen the Father but in that word that's translated.
only in the ESV that you read is really this mononise again.
Yeah, unique. Right, unique, the unique God, right? And there's a there's a
textual variant here. The ESV is kind of updated because they had access to
older forms of text. The oldest form of the text has mononise
fellows. Yeah, the unique God, the unique God. A lot of later texts have
of Manoyanese eos.
Sun, unique Sun, right? For our purposes here of what St. John is saying, it actually doesn't matter which it is. Right. Right.
And our understanding that Christ is God, even in this text, read verse one. Right. Yeah, exactly.
Even if we are to read EOS here, fine, right. We still understand that Christ is God.
But the idea there is the uniqueness, right?
This unique one this unique one who is God and who is the son also
Is the one who has made him known right right throughout history the point here when when John says no one has ever seen
God he's speaking of the father no one has ever seen the father but he is
He's revealed to mankind. He's made known
by the son
That's the by right by the duty got by
the logos the oh by the de barrio wa right which is what we saw in the Old Testament
St John is just
Reading that from the Old Testament right so that means that the person who most spoke to face to face
Is the logos is Christ the person who came and stood by Samuel's bed is
Christ the person who touched Jeremiah's lips is
Christ
That's what Saint John is saying here, right?
And you might wonder like, okay, he's pulling all this out of the Old Testament.
What's new here?
There is something new, which is St. John is identifying Jesus Christ, the Son of Mary,
Born in Bethlehem.
He's saying this one that came and dwelt among us, Tabernacle of Monogamous, is this word
of the Lord whom we've always known.
That's what's going on.
He's making this identification.
That's what's happening here.
Right.
And so then what's going to now unfold in the gospel
proceeds from that point.
This one, the Diabario, the second power in heaven,
this person who was acting all through the Old Testament
became flesh and dwelt among us.
And now here's the story of that.
Yeah, so
And trying to think about ways of
summarizing this in my mind, not that you could really summarize it well, but I mean trying to think about
what I can kind of lodge in my mind to understand especially this phrase the word of the Lord of the Word of God.
You know the first thing that that came to mind for me was that this is talking about
Christ the Son of God in his
revelatory role. Right? This is him reviewing.
revealing God to mankind, revealing the truth.
But it's not quite enough actually.
I mean, it's true. That is true.
Better I think would be to understand that the word of the Lord of the Word of God
is our Lord Jesus Christ as the kind of interface from God to creation.
this is thinking in the top down since this is God reaching out to
his creation. And it manifests in multiple ways, this notion that the Son of God is the Word of the
Lord. So yes, a revelation for sure, right? He speaks and he tells things to the prophets and
teaches the apostles and so forth, right? But as we just saw in St. John's Gospel at the beginning,
creation itself. You know, again, this has got in
interfacing with the creation. The act of creation itself is by the word of the Lord.
Right? He's the one by whom, for whom, through whom all things are made.
Right? And then also, and this was the part that, as you just already heard me, just,
I'm just astonished about this, really. He's not only the one who, in whom we become
as God in whom we, you know, are
devonized, deified, theosis, adopt-
the sons of God, but he sends his light out from the very beginning of creation itself.
This is the Word of the Lord.
Sends that light out so that the humanity that he's about to create would receive it,
would receive the glory that we see in his face, that we receive that light, that love
of God that would transform us and make us in
to the sons of God. There's so many different kinds of language that are used to talk about
our Lord Jesus Christ in Scripture. And it's so appropriate. This episode we're focusing
on this one phrase, the word of the Lord, the word of God. And this to me is the way
to kind of understand, I don't want to say this side of Christ doesn't have sides, but
at least this way of talking about him is that this is
God reaching out to His creation, sometimes to create, sometimes to speak, but always to save
and always from the very beginning to save, to transfigure, to enlighten, to fill us up with
Himself, to, as He prayed in His great high-precly prayer in John 17, that the glory that He received
from the Father before all time will be given then to those who become faithful to Him,
to who are
given this ability to become the sons of God.
And my prayer for all of us is that we would
see and receive that light as much as we're able.
Father Steven.
So there's a couple things here,
but the main one that I kind of want to focus on
is...
What this means in terms of our view of the relationship between Christ and the world and
therefore between Christianity and our lives.
Because we've been taught for a long time to compartmentalize our life, our mental
life, our emotional life, our physical life into these sort of
great sections and to screet areas.
And some of them are not supposed to intrude on the others.
We're told explicitly that that's bad if that happens.
And what that does is it kind of splits our thinking
and our brain and our understanding.
So we think we can understand how to have a successful marriage
or how to raise kids or how to conduct ourselves in the workplace
carry out a career.
or even, you know, be on the parish council at our church, whatever it is, we think we can understand that
without any direct reference to like religion because that's over in its own
category. And of course, Christ is there in that
in that religion category.
But if we take seriously what the Scriptures are telling us
about the Word of God and his relationship to creation,
Thank you.
both at the beginning when it was created,
throughout time and holding it together,
in his interactions with humanity for salvation throughout.
It's about setting an order,
creating and putting things in order, establishing
this rational order of the creation
and within ourselves, such that Christ not only
the agent of that, but he also
is that order? What does that mean? That's rarefied air. What that means is we
can't understand anything if we don't understand and come to know Christ. We
can't understand the simplest task in our everyday life. We can't understand
the experiences we have every day. We can't understand the interactions we have
with other people. We can't understand who we are, what it means to be human. We
can't understand anything how to interact.
how to conduct ourselves, how to conduct ourselves as a community, as a
polity in any context until we come to know Christ. The more we come to know
Christ, the more we ourselves are set in order, and then everything else starts
to fall into place. Everything else starts to make sense because he's the sense
that lies behind it. He's the purpose that lies behind it.
Anything we want to
know anything we want to accomplish, anything we want to heal, anything we want to fix,
anything we want to understand, the only way to that is through Christ. That's coming at
it one way, but it's also true the other way. It's true the other way. One of the other
things that's happened due to that compartmentalization is once you separate these things, once
you separate religion and you separate Christianity from all these other aspects of life, once
they're separated, you can then pit them against...
each other. We have a long heritage, especially in the United States, but probably I'm thinking
elsewhere at least in the West as well, of pitting religion sometimes just referred to as faith,
but pitting religion, pitting Christ, pitting the gospel over against science, learning, academics,
So
The learning of the creation, people have retreated as a result of overreacting to our 19th
century German friends into this kind of trench warfare where you're following one or the
other. But if the reality is that Christ is the sense that lies behind all these things,
Any knowledge that is real knowledge, any knowledge that is true, that expresses
truth is knowledge of Christ. As we come to understand the creation, not just the material
creation vis-a-vis science, but creation in terms of art and beauty and nature and emotional
connections between people, the world around us, the more we come to understand it, the
more deeply it will lead us to no Christ. And this creates a reciprocal relationship, coming
up.
Christ allows us to understand the world in ourselves, coming to understand the world in ourselves,
leaves us to come to no Christ.
When we're healthy and we're doing this effectively.
Any knowledge that seeks to pull you away from Christ or attack your relationship with
Christ or closest to Christ is knowledge falsely so-called.
It's not knowledge.
It's a lie by definition.
Because anything opposed to the truth is a lie.
anything that is the true, that is the true
is of Christ. So that's what I wanted to emphasize. I think this is a very important part where we've
got two more parts of this series to go talking about Christ in the scriptures, especially the Old
Testament scriptures. But to me, this is the especially important part of Christ as the logos that
who in these last days has become incarnate for our salvation.
Amen. Well, that
Our show for today. Thank you very much everyone for listening. If your message did not
get included in this episode, we'd still love to hear from you either via email at Lordofspirits.
at ancientfaith.com or you can message us at our Lordofspirits podcast Facebook page.
We do read everything but cannot respond everything and we do save some of what you send for possible
use in future episodes. And join us for our live broadcast on the
second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific. And if you are on
Facebook.
as Father Stephen again is not.
Like our page and join our discussion group,
leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share the show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it.
And finally, while you're remembering that James Town
preceded the Massachusetts Bay colony,
be sure to go to ancientfaith.com,
Stroke Support and help make sure we
and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much.
Good night and God bless you.
listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength.
honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
The Ancient Faith for the Modern World. This is Ancient Faith Radio.
Hello, this is Metropolitan Grit.
This is...
This ancient faith today with Father Tom Soroka, a weekly live calling show addressing
the issues of our day from a distinctly orthodox perspective.
You can join the conversation by calling in at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-2346.